<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The institutions of the Congregation of the Oratory, at St. Maries in Vallicella, within the city of Rome. Founded by St. Philip Nerius</title>
            <author>Congregation of the Oratory. Santa Maria in Vallicella (Church : Rome, Italy)</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1687</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 157 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 55 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A45924</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing I233A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R215995</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99827750</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99827750</idno>
            <idno type="VID">32173</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A45924)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 32173)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1851:22)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The institutions of the Congregation of the Oratory, at St. Maries in Vallicella, within the city of Rome. Founded by St. Philip Nerius</title>
                  <author>Congregation of the Oratory. Santa Maria in Vallicella (Church : Rome, Italy)</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 106 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Printed at Oxford :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1687.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Catholic Church --  Government --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Oratorians --  Italy --  Rules and practice --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-09</date>
            <label>Leigh Rupinski</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-09</date>
            <label>Leigh Rupinski</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:32173:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE Inſtitutions OF THE CONGREGATION OF THE ORATORY, At St. MARIES in <hi>Vallicella,</hi> WITHIN THE City of <hi>ROME.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Founded by St. PHILIP NERIUS.</p>
            <p>Printed at OXFORD, 1687.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:32173:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:32173:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:32173:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:32173:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>The <hi>Institution</hi> of the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation of the ORATORY in the City</head>
            <p>THE Congregation of the <hi>Oratory</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtituted by Saint <hi>Philip Nerius,</hi> enured rather by practice, than bound by laws, had no peculiar rule according to the cuſtome of Religious perſons, by which to direct their conſultations in managing affairs. For, the pious Father uſing with a paternal affection to govern the deſigns of all ſuitably to their in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clinations, thought it enough to ſee his, alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether inflamed towards piety, to be very fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent in the contempt of all worldly things for the love of Chriſt; and then to approve and confirm as by the Spirit of the Lord thoſe things which by long experience he had found both well to content them, and dayly to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance them in the attaining vertue, and plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing God. This way therefore he was wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thily held fit to diſcover to Secular Prieſts, tho differing from the rules of the Religious, who often profeſſed, the Congregation was not in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtituted by him as its Founder, but by Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:32173:4"/>mighty God, as the author and perfecter there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of. Thoſe things therefore, either which he took care after this manner to be decreed, or which have been, from his firſt inſtitution, by thoſe of our Congregation cuſtomarily ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved, and ever ſince retained, that they may be known in ſhort, are here ſummarily col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected.</p>
            <list>
               <item>Of the <hi>Oratory,</hi> and the Prayer there.</item>
               <item>Of the Church, and the Divine Offices.</item>
               <item>Of the profitable uſe of the familiar Sermons.</item>
               <item>Of the ſtanding rules of the Congregation of the <hi>Oratory.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Of the election, and office of the Preſident, and four Prieſts Deputies.</item>
               <item>Of thoſe that are to be admitted into, or expelled out of, the Congregation.</item>
               <item>Of the breeding of Novices.</item>
               <item>Of the chief practices of the Congregation.</item>
               <item>Of their apparel, and uſual converſe.</item>
               <item>Of the Refectory, and manner of their Diet together.</item>
            </list>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. I.</hi> Of the <hi>Oratory,</hi> and the Prayers.</head>
               <p>WE truly term it the <hi>Oratory,</hi> being a place appropriated to Prayer: (for the familiar handling the word of God, here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:32173:4"/>to be ſpoken of, which was begun in it, but afterward more perfected, and tranſlated into the Church, did not ſo fitly give it that name.) In this place as well ſtrangers, as our own, every evening after <hi>mental</hi> prayer (as we call it) ſay the uſual Litanies; or alſo beſides three times in the week (which is an arbitrary caſtigation of the body) diſcipline themſelves with whips. On Holy-days like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, from the firſt of <hi>November</hi> to the Feaſt of our Lord's Reſurrection, they are here not only by the uſual Prayers, but alſo by a fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliar Exhortation, and a conſort of Muſick, excited to the contemplation of celeſtial things. From Eaſter again to the firſt of <hi>November,</hi> after Veſpers ſung in our Church, and a Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon heard, they repair to ſome appointed place of the Suburbs, or (in caſe hot weather hinders) to ſome Church within the City, there to perform the ſame Spiritual exerciſes. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides, every Sunday, unleſs there be ſome preaching in our Church, the Litanies being ſaid here in the morning, and a ſeaſonable Sermon made after a plain familiar way, chiefly from ſome obſervations drawn out of the Goſpels, thoſe of the Brethren reſort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thither are named, that are to viſit the ſeven principal Churches of the City, and the three publick Hoſpitals of the Sick at certain times that week. The care of all this belongs to the Prefect of the <hi>Oratory,</hi> one appointed out of our Prieſts: or to his Aſſiſtant: either of which are to ſee to the keeping of theſe
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:32173:5"/>Orders, and provide for the ſpiritual benefit of thoſe Strangers that come in, whom like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe they are to inſtruct on Holy-days in their perſonal attendance on the offices of piety to be performed to ſick perſons in the Hoſpitals; and alſo to chooſe out of the Brethren ſome one fit for ſome ſervices of the <hi>Oratory,</hi> and eſpecially a Rector; and to be careful, that in no wiſe theſe infringe that Conſtitution, which the Congregation thought good to deliver in theſe words.</p>
               <p>
                  <q>Let the Prefect of the <hi>Oratory</hi> by no means ſuffer the Brethren, who are choſen Officers therein, to intermeddle in any matter, or bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſs belonging any way either to the place it ſelf, or the Conſtitutions thereof, which he hath not appointed them: for ſuch au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority or power they may not have. And furthermore, that nothing may be innovated hitherto obſerved there, eſpecially concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing all weighty matters belonging to the Ora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory, let the Prefect conſult the Preſident of the Congregation, who hath the ſame power to diſpoſe of the affairs of the Oratory, as of the Congregation.</q>
               </p>
               <p>Enough of this now, to ſhew, after what way the many ſtrangers, that more frequent the Oratory, are to be furthered in contemplation, and the love of heavenly things. But our own, more dedicated to ſuch a purpoſe, are eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally to obſerve that which the Fathers, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructed by St. <hi>Philip</hi> have to this end thus de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creed.</p>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:32173:5"/>
               <p>
                  <q>Let every one have his ſet hours for medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, wherein let him dayly make greater progreſs, affecting and aſpiring after God and things celeſtial; of which the Superiors, according to their Charity and prudence, ought often to admoniſh every one, and mind them of the benefit reaped from theſe exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſes.</q>
               </p>
               <p>Thus thoſe of the Congregation have their ſet times wherein to ſequeſter themſelves for Prayer, and meditation. And beſides the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſident to exhort them, whom they are to hear, they have the Prieſt alſo that is appointed to take the Confeſſions of our Order; who is wont according to his diſcretion either to quicken unto theſe exerciſes any that is too flow, or, when it is requiſite, moderate any too eager.</p>
               <p>But, by reaſon of the many other employ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments beneficial to themſelves and their neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours, they have no other time or ſpace either of the morning, or day, appointed or pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed them for prayer, but what every one at his own choice piouſly and religiouſly ſhall alot for ſuch meditations, and holy devotions. But, at evening, as hath been ſaid, they are duly to meet in the publick <hi>Oratory,</hi> then open for all, even Strangers, and inviting them to Prayer, whence it took its name. But con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the order, and cuſtome of the uſing Prayer, and diſcipline in the <hi>Oratory,</hi> and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the other pious Offices of the Frater<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, we ſhall treat below in the Appendix of this Chapter.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:32173:6"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. II.</hi> Of the Church, and the Divine Service.</head>
               <p>THE Prieſts of the Congregation, as being Miniſters in Divine things, are much in the Church, eſpecially on Holy-days. Some give the divine myſteries to them that come; others, buſied in hearing Confeſſions, quit not their feats from day-break till dinner time, unleſs forced by neceſſity. All the Prieſts ſay Maſs every day, and the reſt ſerve, eſpecially thoſe in Orders; who when Maſs is to be cele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brated more ſolemnly, and with Muſick, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times in the morning deſcending into the Veſtry, with a devout diligence apparel the Prieſts with the ſacred veſtments; and, preſent at the ſolemn Sacrifice, and performing ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral other duties, never depart from the cuſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy of the holy things, nor from the Church, till all Divine Service be finiſhed. As touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the things belonging to the Church, the laws preſcribed to ours are theſe.</p>
               <p>In our Church there ſhall be no Statues of the deceaſed, either of Marble, Braſs, Plaiſter, or any other matter.</p>
               <p>On Holy-days both Maſs and Veſpers ſhall be always ſaid in ſolemn manner. There ſhall likewiſe be ſolemn Veſpers on the Vigils of <hi>Corpus Christi,</hi> on the Nativity of the
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:32173:6"/>Bleſſed Virgin <hi>Mary,</hi> and the Conſecration of our Church on the twenty third of <hi>May;</hi> upon the <hi>Octave</hi> of which the ſame Office is repeated; and within it is renewed unto us the joyful memory of the departure of our Father St. <hi>Philip, viz.</hi> on the twenty ſixth of <hi>May.</hi> Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides, within the Octave of <hi>Corpus Chriſti</hi> the Veſpers every day are to be ſung.</p>
               <p>Likewiſe every year on the twenty ninth of <hi>January</hi> is ſolemnly celebrated the Feſtival of the Holy Martyrs <hi>Papias &amp; Maurus;</hi> and on the morning of that holy day Maſs is ſaid with a Deacon and Sub-deacon attending. The Veſpers are ſung with Muſick both on the Vigil, and on the day it ſelf. Alſo on the <hi>Vigil</hi> the next days <hi>Matins</hi> and <hi>Lauds</hi> are to be ſaid before Supper by our own Prieſts and Clergy; that the due honor be paid to the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trons of our Church and Congregation.</p>
               <p>But, on their Tranſlation, which falls on the eleventh of <hi>February,</hi> tho the ſame be ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved, Maſs and Veſpers are not ſolemnly ſung.</p>
               <p>The Feaſt likewiſe of St. <hi>Gregory,</hi> Pope, and Patron of our Church, on the twelfth of <hi>March</hi> is ſolemnly kept by us, both in the firſt Veſpers, and at Maſs.</p>
               <p>We alſo particularly honour in our ſolemn Church Service thoſe other Saints, with whoſe ſacred Relicks, or ſome more eminent things belonging to them, we have been enriched.</p>
               <p>For we honour with a Double Office, on the twelfth of <hi>May,</hi> the holy Martyrs <hi>Nereus, Achilleus,</hi> and <hi>Domitilla.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:32173:7"/>
               <p>On the ninth of <hi>July Patermuihius, Copres,</hi> and <hi>Alexander,</hi> Martyrs, who have an Altar dedicated to them, with a Semi-double.</p>
               <p>On the firſt of <hi>Auguſt</hi> the Martyr <hi>Pantaleon</hi> with a Semi-double.</p>
               <p>On the twenty firſt of <hi>October</hi> St. <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rſula,</hi> and her Fellow-virgins, Martyrs, with a Semi-double.</p>
               <p>On the fourteenth of <hi>December Spiridion</hi> Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop, and Confeſſor, with a Semi-double.</p>
               <p>Now altho ours in ſaying the Eccleſiaſtical Offices, except only the Veſpers on Feſtival days, do not frequent the Church; yet they are wont to meet in Quire there, when any eminent Anniverſary is kept; as on the day of the <hi>Purification</hi> of the Bleſſed Virgin <hi>Mary,</hi> for Candles; on <hi>Aſh-Wedneſday,</hi> the Principal Faſt, for Aſhes; on <hi>Palm-Sunday,</hi> for Palmes; on the uſual days in the Week before Eaſter at Matins, Maſs, and the other ſolemn Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies of that time. Alſo on the Feaſt of <hi>All Saints</hi> at Veſpers; beſides thoſe uſed likewiſe for the Dead, and at the Matins too; as in the morning at Maſs. Laſt of all on the night of the <hi>Nativity</hi> of our Lord <hi>Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> at Matins, and Maſs.</p>
               <p>After theſe Feſtivals, now to ſpeak of Fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerals.</p>
               <p>When any one of our Congregation dies, every Prieſt is to ſay three Maſſes for the party deceaſed: thoſe, who are not Prieſts, ſhall repeat their Beads nine time; and in the place where the dead body lies ſhall be ſaid the Office
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:32173:7"/>of the Dead: and if it be in the morning, a ſolemn Maſs; if not, it ſhall be ſaid the next day, a Deacon and Sub-deacon attending with ſix Candles lighted on the Altar, and four Torches about the Corps. The Office ended, let two of thoſe lights continue by it till the burial of it. But, if he died in abſence from the houſe, the Night-Office for the Dead ſhall be ſaid by the Prieſts privately: but Maſs ſolemnly, as before. Every year likewiſe with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the Octave of <hi>All Saints</hi> a ſolemn Maſs ſhall be ſaid for all thoſe of our Congregation that are deceaſed.</p>
               <p>Without the conſent of the Preſident and Deputies Maſs ſhall not be ſaid ſolemnly (that is with a deacon and Sub-deacon attending) for any ſtrangers deceaſed; neither ſhall they ordinarily grant it, except he that died were a Prelate; or of eminent rank and quality among the Laity; or elſe very well deſerving from our Congregation.</p>
               <p>No Legacy ſhall be received by the Congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation for ſaying Maſs for every; unleſs per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps there be ſome extraordinary reaſon, and be the full conſent of the Fathers of ten years ſtanding.</p>
               <p>As touching the things which ſeem fit to be here ſet down concerning Confeſſions, we have theſe Orders.</p>
               <p>That every week day one of the Prieſts cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen for this work is to tarry in the Church to hear Confeſſions: but on Wedneſday and Fri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day from morning till dinner time all are to
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:32173:8"/>attend there, and likewiſe on Holy days.</p>
               <p>Yet is none admitted to take Confeſſions, without the conſent of thoſe Fathers, that have lived ten years in the Congregation.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. III.</hi> Of the exceeding great benefit of the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliar Sermons, as well in the Church, as in the Oratory.</head>
               <p>IN our Church, every day, except Satur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day, kept vacant, four of our Preiſts (un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs it be a Holy-day, on which ſome one only preacheth) who are choſen out for this em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployment, each in his turn, fitting their ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions to the capacity principally of the vulgar, and pretending to no pomp at all, or vain popularity, recreate the minds of their auditors with a very beneficial kind of diſcourſe, confirming their matter eſpecially with examples, and approved hiſtories of the Saints. For they are to avoid all difficult que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtions, arguing of opinions, and whatever bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter becomes the Schools than the Oratory. Now, he, who is to take care of this buſineſs, is wont at the appointed time to go down into the Church, and, among other things that are to be prepared, to ſet an Hour-glaſs by the Preachers Seat, and, when he ſees eight or ten auditors aſſembled, to read ſome Book of
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:32173:8"/>wholſome precepts, or elſe compoſed of the ſayings, and lives of the Saints; and, when fifteen, or twenty at the moſt are preſent, to give notice with a Bell at the uſual hour, upon the hearing whereof, he that is firſt to preach haſtens to the place, and, after he hath heard him that reads a while, goes up into a wooden Seat, ſome ſix or eight ſteps high, turns the half-hour-glaſs, which allots him his time, and, making no Preface, begins his diſcourſe upon that ſubject principally, which was read out of the Book. In the midſt of his diſcourſe the Keeper riſeth up to give notice again with the ſame Bell tolled louder; which done, another, who is to ſpeak in the ſecond place, hies him thither, and waits ſo long as till the firſt have finiſhed his diſcourſe. In the ſame manner juſt the third ſucceeds the ſecond, and the fourth the third. Neither is any one of theſe allowed above half an hour; but, when need is, they are put in mind of making an end not only by a glaſs, but by a little bell.</p>
               <p>The Sermons being done, a Sacred Hymn is ſung with Muſick; after which he that ſpoke laſt invites them to ſay three <hi>Pater Noſter</hi>'s, and three <hi>Ave Maria</hi>'s to themſelves, and ſo the aſſembly is diſmiſſed. But, on Sundays, and other Holy-days, one of them, who have ſuch days allotted them to preach on, after Veſpers ſung, makes a Sermon in the Church; who hath power to exceed the half-hour ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, but not their eſtabliſhed rules of diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſing already mentioned. On the ſame
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:32173:9"/>days from the firſt of <hi>November</hi> to the ſolemn Feſtival of our Lord's <hi>Reſurrection,</hi> as alſo on Sundays in the morning, one of ours all the year makes a Sermon in the <hi>Oratory.</hi> But of this elſewhere; it ſufficeth now to relate our Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitutions belonging hereto.</p>
               <p>None of ours may be admitted to make a Sermon in the <hi>Oratory,</hi> without the conſent of the Fathers that have lived ten years in the Congregation.</p>
               <p>No Stranger is to be invited to preach in the Oratory, or Church, but by leave from the Preſident, and the four Deputies.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. IV.</hi> Of the conſtant form of Government of the Congregation of the Oratory.</head>
               <p>NOW we will lay down the State, and Form of our Congregation, that is never to be changed, as it is expreſſed in two de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crees. The firſt of which is compriſed in theſe words.</p>
               <p>
                  <q>Whereas heretofore our Congregation was by divine inſpiration ſo inſtituted by the Holy Father <hi>Philip Nerius,</hi> as to be united only with the bond of mutual charity, not bound with any obligations of vows, oaths, or ſuch like promiſes, as this always was, and, is his, and all the Fathers of the Congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:32173:9"/>their unanimous meaning, that it ſhould ſo continue; it is ordered, that, if at any time any of ours intend to quit this courſe, and to bind the Fathers and Brethren in any bonds of vows, oaths, or promiſes, although theſe ſhould prove the greater part, it may be in their choice, to go into what order they pleaſe, but that the other part, though in number far inferior, do enjoy all the goods of the Congregation in what place ſoever ſituate, ſo long as they ſhall continue in their firſt condition, and that they ſhall not be tied to give any thing of what is, or ſhall be, poſſeſſed, to that other part, that would change it. For ſo ſhall this Congregation be ever preſerved in the Church of God, that is <hi>circumamicta varietate.</hi>
                  </q> Thus far the words of the Decree; that from thence it may ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear, that our Reverend Father in Chriſt could not be perſwaded to lead his Sons any other way, who yet out of his Chriſtian cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity ſo extreamly honoured Religious perſons, and out of his ſingular prudence knew that the holy inſtitutions of ſo many Orders, as have been already founded, were abundantly ſufficient to ſuch as deſired to tye up themſelves by the bonds of vows for attaining the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt excellency of Chriſtian Diſcipline.</p>
               <p>The other Decree is. <q>Leſt, any, under co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour of enlarging the Congregation, ſhould deſtroy it, and that ſuch confuſion, and trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble may be avoided, which a multitude is wont to cauſe, and that thoſe of the Congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:32173:10"/>may be amongſt themſelves more ſtrictly cemented together in the bands of love, which daily converſation begets and nouriſheth; that alſo every ones inclinations may be more exactly diſcovered, and that all may more reverence thoſe perſons, whoſe worth hath been long known to them; it is ordered, that this Congregation ſhall not accept of any place elſewhere, nor under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take the charge of governing any other Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation abroad: and, if any Colledges and Societies in other places ſhall procure our Rules, and deſire to obſerve them, let them not be annexed to ours, nor their Prieſts ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted of the Congregation of the Roman Oratory. But let every Houſe, or Body fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing our form, govern, and manage it ſelf by it ſelf, apart from others.</q>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. V.</hi> Of the Election, and Office of the Preſident, and the four Prieſts Deputies.</head>
               <p>FOR the governing of the Congregation, and taking care of the things belonging to it, firſt a Preſident is choſen, whom we ſtile <hi>The Father:</hi> next four Prieſts are made Depu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties. Of the choice, and offices of all whom the Congregation thus determines.</p>
               <p>None ſhall be elected Preſident, who hath not</p>
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:32173:10"/>
               <p>continued in the Congregation fifteen years, in the which time he hath diſcharged the office of <hi>Deputy</hi> or <hi>Minister;</hi> and who is not at leaſt forty years of age.</p>
               <p>The choice of the Preſident ſhall belong to all the Prieſts of the Congregation; who, after their tenth year paſt, ſhall be admitted to giving their votes: but the Laicks are to know, that they have no power to elect the Preſident, Deputies, and Prefects, but only to perform the duties appointed them by the Rule.</p>
               <p>As well the Preſident, as the Deputies, and other Officers may be choſen in their abſence.</p>
               <p>That Prieſt, that amongſt ours holds the firſt place next to the Preſident in the Congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation, ought to preſide as Superior in the Election, and abſence of the Preſident.</p>
               <p>Now the Election of the Preſident ſhall be after this manner. He that is Secretary ſhall give every Elector Tickets, in which are writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, or printed the names of thoſe that are eli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gible, to put one of them, which they pleaſe, into a Box; two, appointed to that end, look<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing on. Then, as every one is drawn out in the ſight of thoſe two, he ſhall be named aloud by the Secretary; and he ſhall be choſen Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſident, in whole Election more than half the number of the Electors do jointly agree. This way of electing, till they thus agree, they may reiterate ten times; but, after the tenth Scru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiny, if ſtill a greater part than half light not on one, let there be a com-promiſe, namely, that only five of the Electors chooſe a Preſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:32173:11"/>only out of thoſe two, who in any of the trials formerly made have had the moſt voices. Which is ſhewn by an inſtance: For, if two, or more have an eighth part of voices; or one, or more an eighth, and others a ſeventh; then, refuſing all the reſt, the Electors are to chooſe out of theſe only. But the Electors them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, the five Com-promiſers, who have the power of chooſing a Preſident, are only to be elected by a major part of voices of the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation, not required that each have more of the Electors voices than the half: and let them be taken out of thoſe, that were not in nomination at the firſt election. For theſe two at that time have no right at all to any ſuch election, but are deprived of both <hi>active,</hi> and <hi>paſſive</hi> voice, as it is called.</p>
               <p>If at length, when the papers are drawn, the Com-promiſers be even, let him be choſen Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſident, who by his place in the Congregation precedes the reſt of his Competitors.</p>
               <p>The office of Preſident is to laſt three years; and may, at the pleaſure of the Congregation, be confirmed every third year. He ſhall come and ſit down at the ſame table with the reſt, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs ſickneſs hinder.</p>
               <p>He is to have nothing ſingular, either, in the Church, at Table, in Bed, at home, or abroad; except the chief place, and a Laick of our own appointed him by the Deputies, to perform any ſervice he commands.</p>
               <p>As for the eſtate, and goods of the Congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation, he is to menage them carefully, and
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:32173:11"/>to provide things neceſſary for diet, and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parel for ours. To the poor or others, who are not of our Congregation, he may give the value of one Crown every month. For any greater ſumme, as oft as there ſhall be occaſion of ſuch disburſements, he ſhall ask the conſent of the four Deputies: and (if it happen to exceed ten Crowns) of the whole Congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation. The ſame let him obſerve in other extraordinary charges of any work, or other buſineſs, and in all things no way belonging to the proviſion, or dayly uſe of our Houſe.</p>
               <p>The chief power of governing the whole Congregation, and taking care of all things that concern it, is to be in the Preſident; for to him only ſhall belong the aſſembling, when need is, the Congregation; the propoſing things to be debated; the ſeeing good orders executed; the taking an account alſo of things done, or to be done, by any of ours, to whom any office, or charge in what manner, or place ſoever, is committed, and the looking that all things be duly performed. To this end he ſhall call the Congregation of the four Depu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties at leaſt once every week; without whoſe conſent he ſhall do nothing that relates to the publick governing of the houſe, and the chu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing, or removing Officers. For, all the other Officers, and ſervants, who are to continue for three years, ſhall be choſen by the Preſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent; and the four Deputies, except the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſor, to be choſen by a <hi>major</hi> part of the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lectors in the Congregation immediately after
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:32173:12"/>the Preſident, and Deputies being elected: for none of theſe may undertake that charge.</p>
               <p>The Prefects over the ſeveral employments of the Houſe, whom we term Officers, known ſufficiently by their titles, are theſe that follow.</p>
               <p>The Prieſt for Confeſſions.</p>
               <p>The Corrector: one of the Seniors, who privately reprehends the faulty.</p>
               <p>The Miniſter; who, looks to the managing the houſhold buſineſs according to the appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and direction of the Preſident.</p>
               <p>The Prefect of the Veſtry, to whoſe paternal care thoſe aſſigned to the ſervice of the Veſtry are committed, as all the other Laicks are to the Miniſter.</p>
               <p>The Keeper of the Veſtry.</p>
               <p>The Prefect of the Oratory, and his Aſſiſtant.</p>
               <p>The Prefect of the Preachers in the Church.</p>
               <p>The Prefect of Ceremonies.</p>
               <p>The Prefect of the Muſick.</p>
               <p>The two Entertainers of Gueſts.</p>
               <p>The Monitor of the Prayers that are to be made for thoſe recommended at the Table every evening.</p>
               <p>The Prefect of the Novices.</p>
               <p>The Keeper of the Stock-mony.</p>
               <p>The Procurator of the houſhold affairs, and his Aſſiſtants.</p>
               <p>The Library-keeper, and his Aſſiſtant, who are not to permit books to be taken out of the publick Library.</p>
               <p>The Attendant of the Sick, and his Aſſiſtants.</p>
               <p>The Prefect of the buildings, and his Aſſiſtant.</p>
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:32173:12"/>
               <p>Two Prefects, for correcting the errors of thoſe that read at the Table.</p>
               <p>The Prefect of the Apothecary's ſhop, and the Apothecary.</p>
               <p>The Receiver, and Diſpenſer of monies.</p>
               <p>The Keeper of the houſhold goods.</p>
               <p>The Keeper of the Pantry.</p>
               <p>The Keeper of the Wine-cellar.</p>
               <p>The Keeper of the Refectory.</p>
               <p>The Porters.</p>
               <p>All theſe the Congregation particularly ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moniſheth by this conſtitution.</p>
               <p>
                  <q>Let none refuſe any Office impoſed by the Congregation, or the Preſident, and Depu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, but accept it with all ſubmiſſion of mind. And, if he conceive he ought for ſome reaſon to refuſe, after he hath with befitting mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty declared his opinion once, or twice, and the Preſident, and Deputies approve it not, he ſhall without any further excuſe undertake the office enjoyned him.</q>
               </p>
               <p>But, as touching the Deputies to be choſen at the ſame time with the Preſident, thus it is.</p>
               <p>After the Election of the Preſident, ſhall be choſen aſſiſtants to him four of the Prieſts that have lived in the Congregation ten years ſince they were admitted to their firſt probation; and they have power of chooſing out of the whole Congregation; by whoſe conſent, as was ſaid, the Preſident ſhall do all things, which he thinks concern the publick govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Congregation.</p>
               <p>By the ſame Prieſts then (all of ten years
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:32173:13"/>ſtanding) in the ſame manner as above, but proceeding to a third ſcrutiny only, ſhall four Deputies be choſen; each apart, in the ſame Congregation: but, after a third ſcrutiny, without any com-promiſing, let thoſe two be choſen, upon whom the moſt voices in theſe three votings ſhall light. But if more than two, as having equal votes, happen to be thus eligible; only two, the reſt rejected, can be elected: namely thoſe, who of courſe pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cede the others in the Congregation. For example; If, after the third ſcrutiny, one have an eighth number of voices, and another a ſeventh, the reſt not ſo many; we ſay, theſe two are to be preferred to the office of Depu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties by ſcrutiny, the reſt being utterly uneli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gible. And, if many have a ſeventh number; he likewiſe ſhall by ſcrutiny be choſen out of them, excluding others, who takes place in the Congregation. If the votes for the two to be elected be equal again, let him in like manner be taken for Deputy, who of courſe is wont to go firſt amongſt us.</p>
               <p>One of the four Deputies of the three years paſt, (for every ones office laſts three years) or, if it be thought fit, two, may be confirmed for three years more; but after can be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed no longer.</p>
               <p>Out of the Deputies alſo one ſhall be choſen Secretary by conſent of the Deputies them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves; who ſhall write down in a Book made for that purpoſe all the things decreed by the General Congregation, or by the Preſident,
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:32173:13"/>and four Deputies, and write Letters abroad upon occaſions. But all letters, that contain buſineſs, are to be tranſcribed into another Book.</p>
               <p>Beſides; when a Preſident dies, or goes out of his office, the Deputies are to admoniſh the foreſaid Senior, who in the mean time executes his place, to ſummon thoſe that are to be called to the election of a Preſident. And, if he neglect to do it, they ſhall do it them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves.</p>
               <p>If, no man diſſenting, the Deputies ſhall think fit to grant unto, or impoſe upon, the Preſident, for ſome juſt cauſe, a ceſſation from his office; four of the Prieſts of ten years ſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſhall be called in. And, if they alſo ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove of it, let them call a Congregation, by which let him be depoſed, and a new Preſident choſen after the manner aforeſaid; yet ſtill keeping the ſame courſe in depoſing a Preſident, as is appointed to be obſerved in ejecting o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers.</p>
               <p>Every year in <hi>January</hi> one of the Deputies, with another that is no Deputy, ſhall take a particular account of all the expences of the whole year, and, being caſt up, ſhall rehearſe it in a publick Congregation; that the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burſements of the former year may appear to all, and every one may ſee, whether any debt be contracted, and what the Stock and goods of the Congregation amount to.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:32173:14"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. VI.</hi> Of admitting Perſons into, and ejecting them out of, the Congregation.</head>
               <p>THE Fathers of the Congregation, fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing the practice of their excellent Founder, the Bleſſed <hi>Philip,</hi> would have none received for members of their Body, but per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons of good life, very fit and as it were na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turally diſpoſed for their Rule: the Decrees running thus.</p>
               <p>
                  <q>Let none younger than eighteen, or older than five and forty, be admitted to their firſt probation; nor ſuch as the Canons except from Orders, unleſs they mean to continue altogether amongſt the Laity; none ſickly; nor ſuch as have been of any Religious Order; none, but perſons well reported of by all; who have been frequent auditors at the Ora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory, and preſent at the Prayers, and often wont to confeſs to ſome of our Prieſts, and who have made trial of our Rule.</q> Yet, in all theſe, if the Fathers, that have lived ten years in the Congregation, ſo pleaſe, there may be a diſpenſation.</p>
               <p>Two Prieſts ſhall be choſen by the Congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation, who are to be very careful concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thoſe that are to be admitted into the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation, that, before their admiſſion, their
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:32173:14"/>life, and manners be ſtrictly looked into. To this end they ſhall often confer with them, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe with them; and, not herewith content, inform themſelves likewiſe from their Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try men, amongſt whom they have formerly lived. And the two, that are choſen, are to report the information, that they have touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them, to the Congregation being aſſembled again, if it any way concern them to know it, before they privately paſs their votes.</p>
               <p>Beſides the two Fathers, who (we ſaid) were to be choſen for that work, other Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers likewiſe ſhall diligently inquire into the things before ſpoken of; and examine, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they come diſpoſed to continue conſtant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to their lives end in the Congregation, on no other ground, but the ſerving God, and obſerving the rules, and conſtitutions of the Congregation, which therefore the Fathers, before their admiſſion, ſhall offer them to be read, to the end they may the more adviſedly deliberate on the whole buſineſs.</p>
               <p>But, how thoſe that are to be admitted ſhould diſpoſe of their eſtates, and domeſtick affairs, is ſhewn in the eighth Chapter. For, before they be admitted to private ſuffrages, they muſt be in a readineſs to live and dwell with us, leſt, being ſo admitted, they live out of the Congregation, except for ſome few days, at the moſt fifteen.</p>
               <p>Thoſe admitted to the firſt probation ſhall not preſently be reckoned among the Novices, but live a month in our Houſe as gueſts, in
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:32173:15"/>that ſpace the better to learn our cuſtomes, and deliberate more maturely; and on the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſide to try them, whether they be ready to obey in all things, even in the meaneſt and moſt difficult: whether of themſelves they be inclined to the exerciſes of holy meditation, and of the Sacraments; not contentious, not obſtinate, not proud, and refractary in any matter againſt their Superiors, or Inferiors.</p>
               <p>If they make a good proof, after a month their names ſhall be ſet down in a Book ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed for that purpoſe, and from thence ſhall their firſt year of probation commence; in which years ſpace, if their converſation be vertuous, and laudable, they ſhall continue two years in a ſecond probation; otherwiſe they ſhall be diſmiſſed by the Preſident, and Deputies, whoſe office it is to admit to the firſt, and ſecond, probation. And at three years end, if in like manner they ſtill retain the eſteem of having lived vertuouſly in common, they ſhall be voted worthy to be members of the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation. To this therefore by private ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frages they ſhall be aſſociated, and may after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward be choſen into all offices, except that of Preſident, and Deputy. But power of choo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing others they ſhall only have at ten years end; unleſs, by conſent of the Deputies, the Preſident upon ſome grounds think fit to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer it</p>
               <p>And if any of them, upon no other cauſe intervening, but forgetfulneſs, or modeſty, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire not at the due time, what he might eaſily
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:32173:15"/>obtain from the Congregation, when he ſhall be regiſtred in the Catalogue among ours, let him be reckoned as incorporated from that time, wherein the uſual three years, or ten years, ſhall be expired.</p>
               <p>The admitting into the Congregation, and to all the offices above mentioned, ſhall belong to the Prieſts of ten years ſtanding, and ſhall go by the <hi>major</hi> part of voices: but the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitting to the firſt and ſecond probation, as hath been ſaid, belongs to the Preſident, and Deputies.</p>
               <p>None can be expelled the Congregation, unleſs firſt all the Prieſts that have lived ten years therein (reckoning from the day where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in they were admitted to their firſt probation) meet together, and every one give his vote, and that two parts of three determine it to be done. And, if the Prieſts cannot equally be diſtributed into three parts, then the propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion ſhall be obſerved that is of eight to thir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teen, or to fourteen: ſo that, for example, whether the Prieſts be thirteen, or fourteen, two thirds thereof ſhall be eight.</p>
               <p>None may be expelled the Congregation, but for a reiterated, and criminal obſtinacy; or ſome hainous offence; but, what are ſo, it ſhall be ſtood to the judgment of two parts of three, accounting them as before.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="chapter">
               <pb n="28" facs="tcp:32173:16"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. VII.</hi> Of the breeding up of the Novices.</head>
               <p>THoſe that are admitted to the firſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bation, whether inferior Clergy, or Prieſts, are committed to his care, who man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ageth that office in the Congregation, till, the three years being expired, they are reckoned amongſt ours. He directing all unto the good of Souls, beſides that ſpecial queſt after vertue, which ours principally ought to poſſeſs, takes care to propoſe certain other things, which have hitherto been conſtantly obſerv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed: as namely.</p>
               <p>That they ſerve every day at Maſs.</p>
               <p>That, at the appointment of the Superior, they abſtain from the ſtudy of Sciences; which ſtudies are to be moderated in the firſt place, that, endued with heavenly wiſdome, they may learn to love, as to theſe, to be nothing accounted of.</p>
               <p>That they come immediately to the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectory upon the Bell giving notice, and there, according to order, perform the office of Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vitor, or Reader.</p>
               <p>That all of them ſerve, or read, daily, or weekly, both at the firſt and ſecond hour of dinner, or ſupper: but they, who are Prieſts, uſe only to attend at the firſt hour in the morn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</p>
               <pb n="29" facs="tcp:32173:16"/>
               <p>That in like manner they read in the Church before the Sermons, as every ones appointed week falls out: that they be preſent at them, and likewiſe take care that nothing uſually ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved be at ſuch time omitted. And this cuſtome of attending, and reading, let thoſe alſo, who are aſſociated, ſtill obſerve, till they be of ten years ſtanding, or thereabouts, as the Superiors, <hi>viz.</hi> the Preſident, and Depu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, ſhall think fit.</p>
               <p>When the Sermons are done (two of which, or at leaſt one, every day they are to hear) that they may alſo ſomething attend their health, let them recreate themſelves with a walk.</p>
               <p>At Evening let them come to Prayer in the Oratory.</p>
               <p>After dinner and ſupper, for recreation, let all of them for an hour accompany toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in the ſame place with the reſt; and there laying aſide all ſeverity with a pleaſant be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haviour, yet modeſtly, ſo demean themſelves, as that none, tho but in jeſt, touch his fellow.</p>
               <p>If the Porter brings any of them word, that one inquires for him, let him repair preſently to the gate, there diſpatch his buſineſs in few words, bringing in no ſtranger into his cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, or at all into our houſe, without ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainting the Superior.</p>
               <p>Let them neither go out of the houſe, nor go forth alone at any time, but by his leave alſo.</p>
               <p>Let them manage or undertake no buſineſs of Strangers, or any other, which are for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidden
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:32173:17"/>to thoſe that live in the Congregation, either by cuſtome, or ſtatute, without the Preſident's permiſſion.</p>
               <p>Let them on Holy-days ſcarcely upon ur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent neceſſity quit their attendance on holy things, or leave the Veſtry.</p>
               <p>The Altar, which any one hath the charge of, according to the change of the Church-Solemnity let him dreſs up, as ſuites beſt with the time.</p>
               <p>Thrice a week let them confeſs their ſins to the Confeſſor appointed, and thoſe, who are no Prieſts receive the Bleſſed Sacrament, as he ſhall direct.</p>
               <p>Let them take care, if in any thing they err, on their own accord to ſubmit themſelves to correction.</p>
               <p>As touching the Congregation, before which they are to appear, and declare their faults, the conſtitution is this.</p>
               <p>The Congregation for the faults of the <hi>Novi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces,</hi> that is, thoſe, who have not yet lived three years in the Congregation, whether they be Prieſts, or inferior Clerks, ſhall aſſemble, if it may be, every week, namely that they appear before the meeting for general Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion: but, if ſome week there happen no ſuch meeting, let all the Novices aſſemble them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves privately before him, to whoſe care they are committed.</p>
               <p>Sometimes alſo, inſtead of the foremen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned accuſation, they are wont, met toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, to uſe the reading of ſome approved au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor,
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:32173:17"/>by which, thro diſcourſe, and confer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence about Spiritual matters, they may as it were by turns be ſeaſoned with moſt profita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble inſtructions.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. VIII.</hi> Of the principal Cuſtomes amongſt us.</head>
               <p>FOR the cultivating her Childrens minds with a more heavenly diſcipline, and the better conforming them to true Chriſtian Piety, the Congregation chiefly lays down theſe De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crees.</p>
               <p>Thrice a week let every one confeſs his ſins to the Prieſt choſen for that purpoſe (unleſs one be upon good grounds ſometimes permit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by him to do otherwiſe.) Yet the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, ſo inſtituted by St. <hi>Philip,</hi> do much approve, and commend this cuſtome as very beneficial to eternal ſalvation. In like man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner let him ſo often prepare himſelf to receive the Euchariſt; and, if his Confeſſor think fit, receive it.</p>
               <p>The Congregation for faults (as they call it) meet once a fortnight, at which not only Prieſts, but all of the Congregation, Clergy and Laity, ſhall be preſent; where from the loweſt to the higheſt every one accuſeth him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf upon his knees of ſome offence, tho it be a ſmall one, committed by him in common
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:32173:18"/>converſation; and, whatſoever he hath diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſed another in, asks pardon of him. Yet, in this publick accuſation, no mention is made of ſuch ſecret faults as are meet only to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed privately to the Prieſt.</p>
               <p>No Prieſt, who hath not been full ten years a Prieſt in the Congregation, may be the cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rector of others.</p>
               <p>So, on the day appointed all being met to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, the Preſident, as the cuſtome is, firſt by ſolemn Prayers invocating the Holy Spirit, that Prieſt, who in his turn is to correct the reſt (for in this office they uſe to take their turns) called forth ſits down in a ſeat at the Preſidents right hand, and making a ſhort ſpeech before, for the better enflaming their minds towards God, in the ſpirit of meekneſs performs the duty of Corrector: and, whilſt he corrects thoſe of the Clergy, and Prieſts, he remains uncovered; which he uſeth not to be, when he reproves the Laity. He ſtands bareheaded likewiſe in his admoniſhing, and correcting, the Preſident.</p>
               <p>The Laity, and inferior Clerks, when they have accuſed themſelves of their faults, after correction, and a very ſhort admonition from the Preſident concerning ſome vicious cuſtome to be amended, or commendable to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained, preſently depart. Next all the Prieſts, who are as yet Probationers, accuſe themſelves: theſe likewiſe going away, the reſt of the Prieſts take their turn, who, having accuſed themſelves, and received correction, the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſident
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:32173:18"/>returns thanks to God in the accuſtomed Prayers.</p>
               <p>There is to be preſcribed a <hi>Form</hi> of Penan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, as it is termed, which, in the enjoining them, it ſhall not be lawful to exceed. And theſe written in tickets the ſame day, that the faults are acknowledged, at evening in the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectory at the end of ſupper let them be di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtributed to every one out of a bag.</p>
               <p>After this diſtribution, as it falls out, let every one in order, and openly before all, read his own penance.</p>
               <p>Beſides this; as is ſaid before, one of the Seniors ſhall be choſen to perform the continual office of Corrector. Who is privately to cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect every one of the Congregation, even the Deputies, and Preſident: which duty not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding he ſhall diſcharge with all meek<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and lenity of mind, conſidering himſelf (as the Apoſtle ſaith) leſt he alſo be tempted; ſo that he ſeem to endeavour more to reform himſelf, and his own life, that by this means he may reduce his brethen to a better courſe.</p>
               <p>Laſt of all, the care of the diſcipline of the houſe requires, that that week, wherein there is no publick acknowledgment of faults, all the Lay-perſons of the Congregation do meet before the Miniſter to whoſe charge they are aſſigned, to be by him inſtructed, and gently directed in obſerving the way of eternal ſalva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
               <p>Furthermore, to the end ours be none of them infected with covetouſneſs, or corrupted
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:32173:19"/>with ambition, and that by degrees they nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther caſt off modeſty, nor raſhly uſurp autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, proviſion is in ſome kind made by theſe following Conſtitutions.</p>
               <p>To the end, all who are admitted into the Congregation may more diſengaged give up themſelves to God and divine matters, they are in the firſt place to look chiefly, that by no means there be any difference about the eſtates they enjoy; and they are to know, that their yearly profits are to be laid out in ſuch pious uſes as they think fit, and nothing to be hoard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed up; that ſo none of the Congregation may ſet his mind upon getting of riches; nay every one according to his ability is to contribute liberally out of his eſtate, to the common uſe, and benefit of the Congregation. Which thing hath hitherto been ſo carefully obſerved by our Fathers, that, if any one thro poverty hath omitted the paying of the rate appointed, as ſoon as he is any way more enabled he hath not neglected to ſupply and make it up; ſo fitting and reaſonable hath it always ſeemed to them to war every one at his own charge; and to abſtain from the means of the Congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation, as from another mans eſtate, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with ſhe is eſpecially to maintain thoſe of hers who have nothing to live on. Nor may the Congregation therefore be thought to uſe a command over any ones mony, whilſt ſhe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires only the ſet proportion for every ones diet from a cheerful giver; and this too only where their eſtate will bear it.</p>
               <pb n="35" facs="tcp:32173:19"/>
               <p>The Preſident and Deputies may likewiſe remit part of the means alotted by any one, or all of it; if upon any ground they think fit ſo to do.</p>
               <p>Thoſe of the Congregation are forbidden to meddle with all ſecular buſineſs; unleſs when ſome upon a neceſſary cauſe is appointed them by the Preſident, and four Deputies.</p>
               <p>None of ours may (tho requeſted) profeſs under any Congregation or Society out of the houſe, or undertake any charge whatever without leave of the Congregation.</p>
               <p>Whereas there are many in the Church of God, who either do, or conveniently may, employ themſelves in taking the confeſſions of Nuns; therefore, that none be drawn away from the particular deſign of the Congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, it is decreed, that none of ours oblige, or apply himſelf to the hearing the confeſſions, reforming the manners, and managing the buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of ſuch. The ſame we ſay of Seminaries, Colledges, Congregations, Societies, or Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſities, and the intermeddling any way in their affairs.</p>
               <p>No Biſhop, Prelate, nor perſon admitted to any dignity whatſoever, may be received into the houſe of the Congregation to tarry, and dwell there with ours, tho but for a certain time.</p>
               <p>In no wiſe at any time may they ſue for, or accept, any Eccleſiaſtical Benefices: but may keep thoſe they had formerly, if they do not require their perſonal reſidence.</p>
               <pb n="36" facs="tcp:32173:20"/>
               <p>None may take any dignities, but upon the Popes command.</p>
               <p>None without the Preſidents, and the four Deputies conſent may frequent Courts, nor ſeek after offices, or livings for himſelf, or others.</p>
               <p>None may have a ſervant of his own; if any one be in neceſſity, he ſhall acquaint the Preſident therewith, who together with the four Deputies ſhall provide them what is neceſſary.</p>
               <p>None ſhall ſuffer boys to come into his Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, unleſs they be brought in by others, who are preſent as witneſſes; others let them very ſparingly admit, but rather being called let them go down to them.</p>
               <p>None may be admitted to any Eccleſiaſtical Orders without the conſent of the Prieſts that have lived ten years in the Congregation. The ſame holds for preaching publickly, or hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing confeſſions, as elſewhere is ſaid.</p>
               <p>None may put a Book to the Preſs without the Preſidents, and Deputies leave.</p>
               <p>No Statute ſhall be propoſed to be confirm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by the Pope, except the Prieſts of ten years ſtanding firſt conſent thereunto.</p>
               <p>When any univerſal Law is to be made, let all the Prieſts of three years ſtanding be preſent, and have their votes in the conſultation; but in the deciſion only thoſe of ten years ſtanding.</p>
               <p>When any thing is propoſed to be done, let the Fathers beforehand have a publick, and free conſultation about it; then after ſome days their private votes ſhall paſs concerning
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:32173:20"/>it; unleſs perhaps the neceſſity, benefit, or ſometimes alſo the meanneſs of the matter re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire, that it be diſpatched preſently after conſultation by their private ſuffrages. But, as hath been ſaid, tho all the Prieſts of three years ſtanding be admitted, and have a vote in the conſult; yet thoſe only have votes in the decree, who are paſt their tenth year.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. IX.</hi> Of their apparel, and familiar converſe.</head>
               <p>MOreover, for the external modeſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haviour of ours, we exhibit theſe Rules, and Obſervations. Let not them be wanting to apply them alſo for obtaining internal ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues.</p>
               <p>Let none of the Brethren, or Fathers in their apparel wear any ſilk, except a ſhort cloſe Cap upon their Crowns, for keeping their head warm, and a lining to be ſewed to the inſide of their hat.</p>
               <p>Alſo the faſhion of clothes uſed by the Secu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar Clergy ſhall always be obſerved.</p>
               <p>The Laicks ſhall wear a Caſſock down to their knees, and a Cloke ſomewhat longer.</p>
               <p>Thoſe that are cloathed at the Houſe's charge, as oft as need is, are to go to the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter, or, in his abſence, to the Preſident, and acquaint him what they want; and let
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:32173:21"/>them, when appointed to relieve them, with all charitable affection ſatisfy their requeſts.</p>
               <p>In all their apparel, gate, diſcourſe, actions, and geſtures let them obſerve a <hi>decorum,</hi> and every one behave himſelf with all modeſty; but let none of ours ſhew himſelf in any action of his ſingular (as it is called) from the ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary ſort; or in his carriage differ from the common courſe of honeſt, and plain perſons.</p>
               <p>And, tho it be a peculiar cuſtome with us, that (in honor preferring each other, and obeying one another) every one deſires (for abaſing their minds) to take the loweſt place; yet, leſt the order of precedency, and ages, eſpecially in ſitting, and going together pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lickly, and other ſuch like actions, ſhould be confounded; thoſe Prieſts, who are the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niors, ſhall precede: yet ſo, that, if any of the inferior Clergy of three years ſtanding be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moted to Prieſt-hood, he be preferred before the Novice-Prieſts, namely thoſe, who have not lived full three years in the Congregation. And the Laicks muſt always come after the Clergy.</p>
               <p>After Dinner and Supper all perſons of the Congregation are to ſtay together in a place appointed, for the ſpace of an hour, after which let all depart to their Chambers.</p>
               <p>The Senior Prieſts ſhall take their choice of the Chambers that are void; unleſs the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſident and Deputies ſhall appoint otherwiſe.</p>
               <p>None under ten years ſtanding in the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation may go out of the houſe without
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:32173:21"/>the Preſidents leave: for after three years ſtanding to that time the Preſident either him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, or by ſome other, is wont to take the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular care of theſe (eſpecially ſuch as are not yet Prieſts) for their progreſs in vertue.</p>
               <p>None invited out of the houſe to dinner, or ſupper may go, without the Preſidents conſent.</p>
               <p>No Stranger, without the acquainting the Superior, may be invited to dinner, or ſupper; much leſs to lodge in the houſe, but by the joint conſent of both the Preſident, and De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puties.</p>
               <p>None of the Fathers, or Brothers may in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vite any Stranger to any of the country Farms belonging to the Congregation, nor entertain him, to continue there with him, but by con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent of the Preſident of the Congregation.</p>
               <p>None ſhall have leave from the Preſident to be abſent from the Congregation above a month, whether he go into his Country, or elſewhere; except the Deputies likewiſe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent thereto.</p>
               <p>None of the Congregations ſhall be Sponſors for any either in Baptiſme, or any other Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament.</p>
               <p>To theſe may fitly, and pertinently be added likewiſe ſome things, which being by long con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued cuſtome received, and allowed, are ſtrictly obſerved among us.</p>
               <p>As: At Evening in their ſeveral weeks all the Prieſts ſay Litanies in the Oratory.</p>
               <p>At the Sacrifice of the Holy Maſs not only all the inferior Clergy, and Laity daily ſerve,
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:32173:22"/>but many Prieſts (to be commended for it) uſe to be attendants.</p>
               <p>At table, beſides the Laity and inferior Clerks, who conſtantly ſerve by turns, all the Prieſts likewiſe, on their ſeveral days at the evening, do attend.</p>
               <p>Some of ours alſo often repair to the Hoſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tals of the ſick, there by their labour to help the infirm.</p>
               <p>If any fall ſick in the houſe, all often viſit, aſſiſt, comfort, attend on, and confirm him very carefully.</p>
               <p>When any one is near his end, upon notice given, all come together both Prieſts and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, unanimouſly to implore the divine mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy for the dying perſon.</p>
               <p>If at any time one offends another in word; when the matter is decided, at evening in ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per-time he kneels down in the midſt of the Refectory, and, accuſing himſelf as guilty, he craves pardon of him whom he offended; then the other riſing up, and doing ſo likewiſe; at leaſt takes the fault to himſelf, as giving the occaſion thereof: But he that did the wrong is enjoined by the Preſident due penance, which is ſometimes a ſlight one, ſometimes none at all.</p>
               <p>The Penances uſually impoſed on the faults confeſſed twice a month in the Congregation are commonly ſuch as theſe. Kiſſing the feet of the three firſt, or laſt Prieſts at table: Say<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in the midd<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e of the Refectory in a low voice, with their arms extended, the Pſalm
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:32173:22"/>
                  <hi>De profundis,</hi> or the Pſalm <hi>Miſerere,</hi> joining their hands: taking the loweſt place at table: eating their meat ſitting upon the ground: begging on their knees the auxiliary Prayers of thoſe that come into the Refectory: or beg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging them for the expiating their ſins at leaſt by repentance before their death: the craving of every one, as they ſit at ſupper, ſomething as an alms, before their own ſitting down at table: ſerving at the ſecond table; or per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forming at it the Readers office: ſaying their Beads for the Pope, or the Benefactors of the Congregation, or for thoſe of it that are dead: viſiting the ſick in Hoſpitals, and the like.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. X.</hi> Of the Refectory, and their Dieting together.</head>
               <p>IN the laſt place the ordering of the Table in the Refectory, and fitting it for pious converſe, comes to be inſiſted on; where all ours have both the ſame quality, and ſame portion of meat, and drink: It is read ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times at ſupper in Italian, by the Preſident's or Miniſters appointment, ſet down much what after this manner.</p>
               <p>As ſoon as notice is given of dinner or ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per-time, every one giving over his employ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and work, repairs to the Refectory. He is ſilent as he goes to, and alſo as he comes
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:32173:23"/>from, the table to the place where ours are to meet for recreating their minds.</p>
               <p>At his firſt entrance bowing his head, he doth reverence to the ſacred Image before him; then with the wonted expreſſion of reſpect ſaluting the company; every one modeſtly, and ſilently ſtands in his place near the table, neither out of curioſity looking on the diſhes ſerved up, nor on others coming in.</p>
               <p>The Preſident, or he that in his abſence ſupplies his place, after he hath tarried a while till all may come from their chambers, with a plain and diſtinct voice bleſſeth the table in the form preſcribed by the Holy Roman Church; and the Preſident ſits in the firſt place; then the reſt, as every ones order is in the Congregation. If any one come late, yet ſo, as before the Latine lection be ended, ſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing near the door, he ſaith Grace to himſelf, and making his reverence to the Preſident ſits down laſt after all the reſt: for out of honor, and reſpect, the Preſident hath his place in his abſence kept empty on purpoſe at the table, but none elſe. But, after the Latine lection at table, he may not come in, till the cloth being laid again, they be called by the wonted ſignal to the ſecond Table; that thus all may be preſent both at benediction, and giving of thanks. Yet Confeſſors are excepted, who on Holy days have leave to come to dinner, after the reading at the table is ended. At the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of the meal none toucheth any thing on the table, till the Preſident prepare him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:32173:23"/>to eat (who, before he begins, hears about two verſes of the reading.) Likewiſe care is taken, that there be not much noiſe made at the beginning.</p>
               <p>They are all to be content with what is ſet before them at table, asking for nothing more, nor of themſelves bringing ought without the Preſidents, or Miniſters leave; who ſhall free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly beſtow, and provide what they judge ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary, and fitting for every one. If any one want ſome of thoſe things uſually brought, and ſerved up to the table, he himſelf may ask the Servitors for it, tho this better befits him that fits next to him.</p>
               <p>At table ſilence is always obſerved, unleſs ſome exception hinders: for liberty of ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing is allowed to him, that propounds, or thoſe that anſwer, for explicating a doubt.</p>
               <p>Allowed alſo to him, who after ſupper men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions thoſe that are to be recommended to the Prayers of the Congregation: laſt of all to the Preſident, and Miniſter, when any thing falls out which may neither be committed to the Reader, nor ought to be deferred: elſe the law of ſilence is to be obſerved, whereto even the Preſident himſelf is obliged.</p>
               <p>None may read Letters at the table, nor may the Porter bring any, or carry word thereof to any, whilſt eating. If there be any urgent neceſſity, the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>orter, acquainting firſt the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>reſident, or Vice-Preſident with it, by his permiſſion diſpatcheth it. The ſame he is to obſerve till they come from the Refectory
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:32173:24"/>to the place where, for recreating their minds, all are to meet together.</p>
               <p>After meals the cloth taken away, as ſoon as the Preſident riſeth, all riſe and going forth ſtand near the table, ſo that, if it may with convenience be done, thoſe who ſate loweſt ſtand in the midſt, and thoſe who ſate in the middle, ſtand loweſt, all ſtanding in their due order. Only the Preſident for dignity's ſake is a little further diſtant from the reſt. This is the poſture, and order, wherein they uſe to give thanks; which done, they go by couples out of the Refectory; ſo that he who at table ſate next to the<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Preſident goes out with him, and afterwards the reſt, in the ſame order.</p>
               <p>None may tarry at all in the Refectory, or the Porch adjoining, any longer than whilſt they waſh their hands.</p>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>The Reader, and Reading at the Table.</head>
                  <p>Not the body only, but the mind too is to be furniſhed at table with its proper food. Therefore, before other books, the Holy Bible is there read; then ſome kind of pious Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentaries, or peice of Antiquity; laſt of all, at the Superiors pleaſure, another Book, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in either the approved hiſtories of the Saints, or ſome profitable inſtructions in Italian, are contained. The Reader, before dinner or ſupper, makes himſelf and the books ready for reading on the desk; where he ſtands bare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>headed,
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:32173:24"/>whilſt prayers are ſaid at the table and having pronounced the verſe, <hi>Jube Domine benedicere,</hi> and tarried till all be ſet, ſitting down himſelf with his head covered, and held upright, he reads aloud, diſtinctly, and plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly. The whole reading being diſcreetly di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtributed into its parts, he ceaſeth not reading of the laſt till commanded by the Preſident; nor doth he command him till above half dinner, or ſupper be paſt. The reſt of the time at table is ſpent in putting a queſtion, as the manner is, and clearing it by anſwers. The Reader is not only at table to read the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentioned Books, but to invite them to the putting of ſome doubt: likewiſe every week once at leaſt to rehearſe the names of our Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefactors; laſtly to publiſh whatſoever he ſhall be enjoined, either in word, or writing, by the Preſident, or Miniſter. For, he may nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther read, nor pronounce any thing more, than what is by them impoſed upon him. The Reader, when corrected, is to repeat the Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectors words with the ſame pronunciation of the ſyllables as he gives them: and the Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rector choſen for this purpoſe is to word mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaken, without the interpoſing any other words.</p>
                  <p>When he hears the Preſident ſay, <hi>Etreliqua,</hi> the Reader gives over. Then ſaying the verſe, <hi>Tu autem Domine miſerere nobis,</hi> and giving no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice aloud to the Prieſt, who, in his turn, is to propoſe ſome doubt, he goes down, and
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:32173:25"/>making an obeiſance to the Preſident ſits down to meat.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Doubts to be propoſed at Table.</head>
                  <p>After reading preſently ſome one of the Prieſts (for all of three years ſtanding in the Congregation are wont to do the ſame) every day, morning, and evening, propounds ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing out of the Scriptures, or Morality, or inſtructions for right informing the mind, and conſcience, that may be queſtioned, or diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted: but avoids the putting any thing diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cult, obſcure, or too curious, to which all are not able to ſpeak. Yet if at any time one make no other anſwer, ſave that he ſtands to the common judgment of the reſt, it is rather to be imputed to modeſty, than ignorance. And he that is to do that office, when his day comes, propoſeth the queſtion of himſelf, tho the Reader, according to the cuſtome, do not advertiſe him: yet, if any ſtranger invited be at the table, not without the command of the Preſident, or his Subſtitute , for then, the Reader is not, as at other times, to put him in mind. If the Proponent be abſent, he is to ſucceed him, who uſeth to ſit next him at table. If any be long e're he propoſe the caſe, either thro forgetfulneſs, or neglect, coming unprovided, the Preſident is either to demand it aloud of him, or to mind him thereof by the whiſper of ſome one that ſits near him. The difficult queſtions propoſed at Table are uſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:32173:25"/>two: every one ſpeaks to one, or other there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of; but the proponent in the laſt place, to remove all doubt, makes a premeditated an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer to both. The firſt Anſwerer is to be he that ſits next below the Proponent at table; then the other Prieſts of full three years ſtanding in the Congregation in like order. Let the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwers (which are to be very ſhort) have no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of flouriſh, and oſtentation: for the doubt is propoſed as it were in the name of the whole company, to have it explained; that every one, even the propoſer himſelf, may anſwer to it, as a Scholar, examined by his Maſter.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>An Appendix.</head>
                  <p>Laſtly; Concerning the Conſtitutions them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves it is ordered thus.</p>
                  <p>If there be any thing dou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ful in our Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitutions, the Preſident, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>d Deputies ſhall clear it: yet by no means may they change, or impair them, nor in any wiſe innovate, or make new ones.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>An Appendix to the firſt Chapter purpoſely ſet by its ſelf.</head>
                  <p>In the Oratory everyday at evening, upon tolling a Bell, a lamp and candles being lighted, and an hour-glaſs ſet upon the Altar before the Image of our Bleſſed Lady, from the ſolemn Feaſt of our Lord's Reſurrection, till the firſt
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:32173:26"/>of <hi>September,</hi> the hour before Sun-ſet, and from the firſt of <hi>September</hi> to the Feaſt of <hi>Eaſter</hi> the firſt hour after Sun-ſet, is appointed for Prayer: but on Holy days, from the firſt of <hi>November,</hi> the ſecond hour too; for then there is both a Sermon, and Muſick.</p>
                  <p>Now the manner of the Prayers is this; after they have ſpent half an hour ſilent in <hi>mental</hi> Prayer, as it is called, the Sacriſtan lighting the reſt of the candles upon the Altar, and giving notice, the Prieſt, whoſe week it is to officiate, begins the Litanies, alternately with him recited by the company aſſernbled, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepting the following prayers pronounced by him alone: Who, when he comes to the Prayer for Peace, which begins, <hi>Deus a quo ſancta de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideria</hi> &amp;c. prefently two of the Brothers, or Miniſters of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Oratory, taking from off the Altar two little <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ictures of our Bleſſed Saviour firſt give them to the Prieſt kneeling to kiſs: he kiſſing them both, and ſaying on the one ſide, and the other, <hi>Pax tecum,</hi> they bowing their heads anſwer, <hi>Et cum spiritu tuo:</hi> and afterward offer them to be kiſſed by all that are in the Oratory, with the like ſalutation [<hi>Pax tecum</hi>] as the Prieſt uſed. The reſt of the prayers in the mean while being ended, he deſires them all aloud to pray to God for per-ſevering conſtantly in his worſhip and ſervice, ſaying to themſelves five times the Lord's Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, and the Angelical Salutation: his words are, <hi>Petamus quaeſo, nobis in divinis perſeveran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiam, recitantes</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Let us I beſeech you, beg
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:32173:26"/>perſeverance in things ſpiritual, rehearſing</hi> &amp;c. Theſe Prayers ended, he again deſires them to repeat them both again twice for the Pope, Cardinals, and other more eminent Prieſts; for the concord of Chriſtian Princes, propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation of Faith, extirpation of Hereſies, and for obtaining the converſion of wicked livers; Then again to recite them once more for the Brethren of the Oratory that are deceaſed, begging for them eternal reſt. Afterward ſaying the verſe, <hi>Dominus det nobis ſuam pacem,</hi> he repeats an <hi>Antiphon</hi> of our Bleſſed Lady, either <hi>Salve Regina,</hi> or ſome other beſt ſuting to the time. At laſt they, who with theſe ſacred Images have ſaluted firſt the aſſembly, and then mutually themſelves with the kiſs of peace, relate to the Prieſt what things they have received from them to be at that time recommended to their prayers; who there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon intreats all that they would be pleaſed to ſay one <hi>Pater,</hi> and <hi>Ave,</hi> for thoſe particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars, and five times invoke the moſt Holy Name of <hi>Jeſus.</hi> Which done, ſo ſoon as he hath pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounced the verſe <hi>Divinum auxilium maneat ſemper nobiſcum,</hi> and all have bowed themſelves even to the kiſſing the very ground, the Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly is diſſolved.</p>
                  <p>This is the conſtant order of the Prayers, excepting Mondays, Wedneſdays, and Fridays, and the whole week before Eaſter: for on theſe days, in memory of the ſcourging wherewith our moſt innocent Lord Chriſt <hi>Jeſus</hi> for our ſakes was puniſhed, they all whip themſelves
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:32173:27"/>in the Oratory. And the cuſtome, and manner is (unleſs theſe days be Holy days, of fall in Eaſter week) that after half an hours <hi>mental</hi> prayer (as they call it) made ſecretly, ſtraight ſome of the Keepers, or Officers of the Ora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory diſtribute whips made of ſmall cords, full of knots, put forth the children (if there be any) and carefully ſhut the doors and win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dows, and extinguiſhing the other lights, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept only a ſmall candle ſo placed in a dark lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thorne upon the altar that the Crucifix may appear clear and viſible, but not reflecting any light, thus make all the room dark. Then the Prieſt in a loud and doleful tone pronoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceth the verſe <hi>Jube Domine benedicere.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <q>
                     <p>The Paſſion of our Lord <hi>Jeſus</hi> Chriſt be ever in our hearts.</p>
                     <p>Remember, Dear Brethren, that our Lord <hi>Jeſus</hi> Chriſt was for us ſold, betrayed with a kiſs, led firſt to <hi>Annas,</hi> then to <hi>Caiphas</hi> the High Prieſt, and at laſt to <hi>Pilate</hi> into the Judgment Hall, where he was bound to a Pillar, and ſcourged; crowned with a crown of thorns, and clothed with a purple veſture; buffeted, and ſpit on, and delivered to the Jews to be crucified; brought to Mount <hi>Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vary,</hi> and crucified, and with him two thieves, one on the right hand, the other on the left; and when he ſaid <hi>I thirst,</hi> they reached him vinegar, which having taken he ſaid <hi>It is finiſhed,</hi> and bowing down the head gave up the ghoſt. [<hi>Here every one with his fiſt beats his breast</hi>] Afterward one of the Soldiers
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:32173:27"/>with a ſpear peirced his ſide, and ſtraightway iſſued out blood, and water; and being taken down from the Croſs, he was buried in a new tomb; and the third day roſe from the dead. <hi>Tu autem Domine miſerere nobis.</hi> They anſwer; <hi>Deo gratias.</hi> Then follows: Serve the Lord with fear, and rejoice unto him with trembling: <hi>Apprehendite diſciplinam</hi> &amp;c.</p>
                  </q>
                  <p>At which words taking their whips they ſcourge their naked bodies during the time that the fiftieth Pſalm <hi>Miſerere</hi> with the <hi>Gloria Patri, &amp;c.</hi> and the 129. <hi>De profundis</hi> (at the end of which is ſaid, <hi>Requiem aeternam &amp;c</hi>) be devoutly by turns recited: Likewiſe during the prayers, <hi>Fidelium Deus omnium conditor, &amp; redemptor </hi> and, <hi>Deus qui culpâ offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deris </hi> at the concluſion of which, upon a ſign given, they end their whipping. Then the Prieſt requeſts them to repeat the Lord's Prayer and Angelical Salutation five times: after that, twice for the Pope <hi/> and once for the faithful departed <hi/> ſo as they are wont to do on other days, when they uſe no diſciplining. Meanwhile in this ſpace they all put on their clothes in the dark, and in ſilence. After this they ſay by turns the Song of <hi>Simeon, Nunc dimittis ſervum tuum Domine.</hi> In the mean time the Keeper of the Oratory makes him ready againſt he hears thoſe words, <hi>Lumen ad revelationem gentium</hi>  when opening his lanthorne he lights the candles anew. The Prieſt who officiates goes on praying, <hi>Da pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cem Domine</hi>  and, that Prayer being end<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed,
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:32173:28"/>
                     <hi>Deus a quo ſancta deſideria</hi> &amp;c. the holy Pictures are preſented to be kiſſed in token of peace, after the ſame manner, as on other <hi>Feria's.</hi> Meanwhile the other prayers follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing being added, he that prayeth ſaith, <hi>Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus det nobis ſuam pacem:</hi> to which they anſwer, <hi>&amp; vitam aeternam Amen.</hi> In the laſt place they ſalute the Holy Virgin Mother of God with an uſual <hi>Antiphon,</hi> ſuch as befits the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular ſeaſon of the year: and ſo the reſt, as in other <hi>Feria's,</hi> wherein they uſe no whip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pings at all.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>The Exerciſes wherein they are em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed on Sundays.</head>
                  <p>On Sundays the Sacriſtan, or ſome of the Keepers, betimes in the morning opens the Oratory doors; the Reader prepares to read in ſome book of ſome good ſubject and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable diſcourſe, till, the company increaſing, the Prefect, or his Aſſiſtant, all kneeling down, propoſeth ſomething for their pious medita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: after this he goeth on with the Litanies, and other prayers, as is every day the cuſtome there at Evening to do. Theſe ended, ſome one of the Prieſts, that are not then appointed to hear confeſſions, making a Sermon upon the Goſpel for the day in a plain ſtile, and not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove half an hour long, exhorts his auditors to the avoiding ſin, the keeping up good cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtomes, and in fine to the conſerving all piety. The Sermon ended, and the Lord's Prayer
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:32173:28"/>and Angelical Salutation rehearſed, the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect asks, whether any of the company knows any of the Brethren ſick, that he may preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly diſpatch ſuch as are appointed, or as he likes beſt, to viſit, and comfort the party lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhing, releive his ſadneſs or want, exhort him to the confeſſing of his ſins, and the bear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his pain patiently and chearfully. The ſick Brothers name, and dwelling is writ down in a table, that the offices of viſiting and pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing for him be not omitted. Then ſeven of the Brothers are ſent to the ſeven Churches of the City famous all the world over for devo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and the ſeveral Indulgences of Popes; and three to the three publick Hoſpitals of the ſick; that ſo each of them may once a week viſit either the Church, or Hoſpital, that falls to his lot: for on Holy days almoſt all attend on theſe offices of Piety. And in theſe exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſes they ſpend about an hour and a half. Alſo on the laſt Sunday of every month they are put in mind to prepare themſelves for the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion, to receive the Holy Euchariſt: for every firſt Sunday in the month they arm them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves with this Sacrament; and in the after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noon [i. e. <hi>at Vespers</hi>] either certain brief inſtructions written in tickets, or paper pictures of ſome Saints are diſtributed in the Oratory, for every one to take one, and learn by that which is written underneath what he is to requeſt of our Lord by means of that Saint whoſe picture is fallen to him.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <pb n="54" facs="tcp:32173:29"/>
                  <head>The Afternoon Exerciſes both for Sun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>days and Holy-days.</head>
                  <p>On all Holy days after <hi>Vespers</hi> ſung in the Church, and a Sermon made, many of ours, Prieſts, and Laicks, with the Brethren of the Oratory and divers others, meet in an ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed place in the Suburbs, where, ſitting down on the graſs, firſt thoſe that are skil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful ſing ſome pious or ſacred hymn; then ſome one ſays by heart a Sermon adorned no leſs with Piety, than elegancy, given him in writing by the Prefect of the Oratory: which done, they ſing again. After this the Prefect of the Oratory riſeth up, or ſome other thereto ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed by the Fathers, who, propoſing very briefly a ſubject concerning living vertuouſly and chriſtianly, invites a ſecond to diſcourſe thereon; then a third; and, if the time per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit it, a fourth: who all of them ſpeak to the matter propounded with equal brevity, and piety, to the benefit of both themſelves, and their auditors. When it is time to conclude their diſcourſe, a hymn is ſung, and ſo all re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn home, or to the Oratory. And, when they cannot go to ſuch places for extream heat in Summer, they repair in ſome Church to thoſe their exerciſes. But in Winter, from the firſt of <hi>November</hi> to Eaſter, on Holy days at evening, when the <hi>Ave-Mary</hi>-Bell rings, they go into the Oratory. Half an hour mental prayer laſts; Litanies are ſaid or ſung with
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:32173:29"/>muſick; our Lord's Prayer and the Angels Salutation repeated according to the uſual num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber (but, when there is muſick, rehearſed only thrice;) then the <hi>Antiphon</hi> of the Bleſſed Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin, which is changed according to the ſeaſon; and laſtly ſome pious ſong ſet to the muſick is ſung. After this one of our Prieſts, as it hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pens to be his turn to preach, with as much profit and plainneſs as may be, diſpenſeth to the people preſent the word of God for half an hour: after that the muſick again: then they pray to God in the uſual form thrice; ſalute the Virgin Mother; and ſo the Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly is diſmiſſed.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>The employments of the Strangers in the Oratory.</head>
                  <p>Out of the Strangers, who are Brethren of the Oratory, firſt the Prefect chooſeth a Rector to overſee the offices of the reſt; two or four Sacriſtans, or Keepers, to ſweep the Oratory, light the Lamps, and Candles, take care of the diſciplines, Clock, and dreſſing the Altar. Likewiſe two or four tenders of the ſick, who are to viſit the Brothers that are ill; ſome are alſo choſen, faithfully and carefully to diſpoſe of the mony voluntarily offered either for the benefit of the ſick Brothers, or of the Hoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitals, or of the Oratory; and they are by no means to receive any, unleſs they know it be freely offered; obſerving that of the Apoſtle <hi>Non veſtra, ſed vos: Not yours, but You.</hi> One likewiſe is choſen Secretary, to regiſter all
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:32173:30"/>things to be debated-of. A Reader alſo, who on Holy days reads ſome pious leſſons before the Prayers. Beſides, every Holy day they carry to the ſick in the Infirmaries things con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducing to their recovery approved-of by the Phyſitian.</p>
                  <p>Every month, or oftner, if they pleaſe, they are to report the ſumme of their disburſements, according to the orders given them, to the Rector, and Prefect of the Oratory; for theſe Strangers, and Lay-Brethren have no autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity or power in diſpoſing the things belong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the Oratory, but only in the diſpenſing them by the direction of the Prefect.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>The Order in electing theſe Lay-officers.</head>
                  <p>Every four months the Brethren, that are Strangers, are choſen to theſe Offices in this manner. After rehearſing the Lord's Prayer and Angelical Salutation, the Prefect is wont in this form to implore the Divine aſſiſtance: <hi>Veni Creator Spiritus, reple</hi> &amp;c. Anſwer is made: <hi>Et tui amoris</hi> &amp;c. V. <hi>Emitte Spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>um tuum, &amp; creabuntur.</hi> R. <hi>Et renovabis fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciem terrae.</hi> The Prayer, <hi>Deus, qui cordafide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lium</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Actiones nostras</hi> &amp;c. As ſoon as they are declared, and publiſhed, <hi>Te Deum</hi> is ſaid; an <hi>Antiphon</hi> of our Bleſſed Lady; the Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, <hi>Gratiam tuam</hi> &amp;c. the Antiphon, <hi>Da pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cem</hi> &amp;c: the Prayer, <hi>Deus, a quo ſancta defi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deria</hi> &amp;c. And the Prayer of that particular Sunday, or of the Saint, whoſe Feſtival is
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:32173:30"/>is then kept. Then ſome pious directions or in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructions are briefly read to the perſons elected.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>An Advertiſement concerning the Conſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of the Congregation.</head>
                  <p>Seeing that the Congregation hath power to eject, and expel out of the ſociety and houſe, all enormous offenders or diſturbers of its or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders; and ſeeing that it is likewiſe very proba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, that whoever neglects his own ſalvation will hardly continue long there, where is to be both a daily advancement in vertue, and a pious emulation of the moſt perfect, the Holy Founder hath declared his intent, that theſe conſtitutions ſhould not oblige any one under ſin. God the great Arbiter, who will beſtow on every one eternal rewards according to their piety, in his great mercy be propitious unto us. <hi>Amen.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <trailer>Here end the Rules of the Congrgation of the bleſſed <hi>Philip,</hi> or of the Roman Oratory of St. <hi>Maries</hi> in <hi>Vallicella,</hi> compoſed, reviſed, and confirmed by the authority of the Holy See Apoſtolick.</trailer>
               </div>
               <div type="prayers">
                  <head>Prayers uſed before a Congregation.</head>
                  <p>
                     <q>Come Holy Ghoſt repleniſh the hearts of thy faithful; and kindle in them the fire of thy love.</q>
                  </p>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>V.</speaker>
                     <p>Send forth thy Spirit, and they ſhall be created.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>R.</speaker>
                     <p>
                        <hi>And thou ſhalt renew the face of the earth.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <pb n="58" facs="tcp:32173:31"/>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>V.</speaker>
                     <p>Remember thy Congregation.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>R.</speaker>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Which thou haſt poſſeſſed from the beginning</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>V.</speaker>
                     <p>O Lord hear my Prayer.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>R.</speaker>
                     <p>
                        <hi>And let my cry come unto thee.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>V.</speaker>
                     <p>The Lord be with you.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>R.</speaker>
                     <p>
                        <hi>And with thy Spirit.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <q>
                     <p>Let us pray.</p>
                     <p>God, that haſt taught the hearts of the faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful by the illumination of the Holy Ghoſt: grant us in the ſame Spirit to underſtand the things that are right, and always to joy in his conſolation.</p>
                     <p>Prevent our actions, O Lord we beſeech thee, by thy favour, and further them by thy help: that every Prayer, and work of ours may be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin always from thee, and begun may end in thee, Thro Chriſt our Lord. <hi>Amen.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </q>
               </div>
               <div type="prayers">
                  <head>Prayers after a Congregation.</head>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>V.</speaker>
                     <p>But thou O Lord have mercy upon us.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>R.</speaker>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Thanks be unto God.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <p>Let us pray.</p>
                  <p>O God, whoſe property is alway to have mercy, and to ſpare, receive our petition; that, if in this Congregation we have committed any error, the clemency of thy piety may pardon it, Thro Chriſt our Lord. <hi>Amen.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Our Father <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>V.</speaker>
                     <p>And lead us not <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>R.</speaker>
                     <p>But deliver us <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>V.</speaker>
                     <p>From the gate of hell.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>R.</speaker>
                     <p>Deliver them O Lord.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>V.</speaker>
                     <p>Let them reſt in peace.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>R.</speaker>
                     <p>Amen.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>V.</speaker>
                     <p>O Lord hear my Prayer.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>R.</speaker>
                     <p>And let my cry come unto thee.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <pb n="59" facs="tcp:32173:31"/>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>V.</speaker>
                     <p>The Lord be with you.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>R.</speaker>
                     <p>And with thy Spirit.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <q>
                     <p>Let us pray.</p>
                     <p>O God, the beſtower of mercy, and lover of mans ſalvation, we humbly beſeech thy cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mency, grant, that the brethren, relatives, and benefactors of our Congregation, who are departed out of this world, may by the inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion of the bleſſed and perpetual Virgin <hi>Mary,</hi> and of all thy Saints, attain to the fru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ition of eternal felicity, Through Chriſt our Lord. <hi>Amen.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Let the ſouls of the faithful thro the mercy of God reſt in peace. <hi>Amen.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Glory be to God.</p>
                  </q>
               </div>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="60" facs="tcp:32173:32"/>
            <head>Memorable Sayings and Advices of St. PHILIP NERI Tranſlated out of an Italian Copy.</head>
            <p n="1">1. THE Devil, who is a moſt proud Spirit, and a lover of darkneſs, is no way better conquered than by humility of heart, and by manifeſting ſimply and clearly without any concealment all one's ſins and temptations to their Confeſſor.</p>
            <p n="2">2. According to the rules of the Fathers and ancient Monks, he, that will make advancement in Religion, muſt diſ-eſteem the world, muſt eſteem all others in it, not value himſelf; not value that he is not valued.</p>
            <p n="3">3. God evermore ſearcheth into the hearts of men for the ſpirit of humility, and a mean eſteem of ones ſelf; nor is there any thing more diſpleaſing to him, than a ſwoln conceit of ones own worth.</p>
            <p n="4">4. When one commits a ſin, or falls into ſome overſight; he ought preſently to imagine, God permitted this his fall becauſe of his pride.
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:32173:32"/>And ſurely to excuſe ſuch a defect, is a thing very dangerous; therefore who thus falls ought ſo often to ſay; <hi>Had I been humble I had not fallen.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">5. When one is reprehended for ſome fault committed, he ought with all chearfulneſs and humility to entertain ſuch reproof, and not to become ſullen and diſcontent upon it; becauſe ſuch a pettiſh diſcontent, which out of a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain pride thinks much to be corrected, is more miſchiefous than the fault it ſelf.</p>
            <p n="6">6. We ought not to demand of God to viſit us with afflictions and temptations out of a pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumption of our own ability to conquer them; but well may we requeſt of him, with an hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and confident affection, grace and ſtrength with chearfulneſs to undergo whatſoever he ſhall pleaſe to inflict.</p>
            <p n="7">7. When a man is afflicted by any infirmity or indiſpoſition of Body, he ought to bethink himſelf ſeriouſly and ſay; God hath laid this weakneſs on me, becauſe of ſomething he would have to be done by, or amended in, me. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I reſolve to change my courſe of life (but this by his aſſiſtance) and become a better man.</p>
            <p n="8">8. Faſting, uſing of diſciplines and ſuch like other penances, ought to be done by advice of one's Confeſſor. For whoſoever do them of their own head, may either wrong their com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plexion, or may by doing them become proud, thinking themſelves to have done ſome great matter. We muſt ſeek after knowledge, but without curioſity or anxiety; and that which
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:32173:33"/>we learn ought to be kept ſecret, making no oſtentation of it, but uſing it to better our life.</p>
            <p n="9">9. A mans heart is arrived to great per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection, when it is diſcreet and paſſeth not the limits of what is convenient Therefore many (eſpecially of thoſe who begin to ſerve God) for want of this diſcretion apply them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves ſuddenly to a moſt auſtere life, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertake moſt tireſome penances; by rigorous faſtings, putting on the rougheſt ſackcloth, ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing on boards, watching and praying whole nights, when ſuch things are diſproportional to, and much exceeding, their ſtrength; ſo that in ſome time they remain confounded, and indiſpoſed both in reſpect of body and mind.</p>
            <p n="10">10. We may not ſo apply our ſelves wholly to the means, as to forget the end for which the means were uſed. Therefore they err ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedingly who are only intent on mortifying the body with abſtinences, whippings, pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grimages, hair cloth, or ſuch like, and there ſtay, imagining now they have done all; And know not that all this is nothing if theſe means do not promote us to fear God, to keep, with a love to them, his Commandments, and to humble us, and to wean us wholly from the world, that with our whole heart we may ſerve him.</p>
            <p n="11">11. Some there be who by little and little much over-charge themſelves, tasking themſelves to ſay every day their Beads, ſeveral times the hours of the bleſſed Virgin, the office of the
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:32173:33"/>Dead, and divers Prayers ſome for one man, ſome for another, and the like, all which may haply be good, but altogether are too much; and ſtraining themſelves to perform them, in the end through tediouſneſs they give them over. Beſides that ſo many things to be done hinder mental prayer. Therefore 'tis beſt to chooſe ſome good courſe of devotion, and ſo continue to practice it, and not afterward to leave it off.</p>
            <p n="12">12. We muſt not do all things in a moment, nor become Saints in three or four days; but by little and little and from one degree to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother.</p>
            <p n="13">13. There is more difficulty to remedy thoſe who will do too much, than to incite others who do too little.</p>
            <p n="14">14. It is very profitable to intermit ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times one's uſual devotions, when his Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſor adviſeth it. If it ſo fall out that his Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſor adviſeth him not to communicate on his accuſtomed days, but defer it to another time, and the perſon thus adviſed will not obey, but is reſolute ſtill to communicate, and is diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſed with what is commanded him; this is not devotion but a ſign of hard-heartedneſs, of little mortification, and of pride, by which he is rendred moſt unworthy of that Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
            <p n="15">15. When one knows how to countermand his own will, and to deny to his ſoul its own de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires, he is in a good degree of vertue. But not to know and not to ſtudy to do this, is to
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:32173:34"/>carry about one the ſeminary of a thouſand temptations; and ſuch a one will be apt to take offence, and to break friendſhip, and will ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome be chearful, but for the moſt part Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lancholy and troubled for the things that will befall him.</p>
            <p n="16">16. External devotion is no certain ſign that one is truly devout, neither are tears them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves always a true ſign of devotion; becauſe ill women eaſily weep, yet are no Saints for it.</p>
            <p n="17">17. If from any perſon one receives a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulſe, he ought by no means to take it ill, or ſhew ſign of diſcontent, but continue towards them the ſame chearful countenance, as for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly, and to take from them all ſuſpition of his ſmall ſatisfaction.</p>
            <p n="18">18. When it is needful to admoniſh any per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of quality of ſome notable defect, the beſt way is to let the reprehenſion fall on ſome third perſon, for ſo they will more eaſily and gent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly take it to themſelves; and not be angry that one ſhould dare to play the Maſter over them.</p>
            <p n="19">19. Who would be much obeyed, let him not command too much.</p>
            <p n="20">20. Then the obedience is good when one obeys without arguing, and holds it for a rule, that what is commanded is fitteſt to be done. And whoſo enters into a Society ought to be moſt ready to obey; and to leave all private, for the common, affairs.</p>
            <p n="21">21 It is not enough only to honor our Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periors, but we ought alſo to honor our equals and our inferiors, and to ſtrive to be the firſt in giving honor.</p>
            <pb n="65" facs="tcp:32173:34"/>
            <p n="22">22. It is a thing appertaining to virtue to fly all manner of ſingularity, and not to make ſhew to be, or to do, any thing more than o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers.</p>
            <p n="23">23. Raptures, Extaſies, and tears in publick, and in the ſight of people, are ſuſpicious; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe Grace loves the receſs and privacy of the heart, except ſo far as it is neceſſary to mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt it for the good of our neighbour; and Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture ſeeks her own, and loves to make an out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward ſhew and appearance.</p>
            <p n="24">24. We ought not to delay to do well, for death delays not to approach; and happy is the young man to whom God gives time to be able to do good.</p>
            <p n="25">25. Idleneſs is a peſtilence to a Chriſtian; and therefore muſt we always be doing ſomething, eſpecially when alone in our chamber: either reading ſome book of Devotion, or the lives of Saints, or the H. Scripture; or ſaying our Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, or ordering our books, or making our bed, or ſome ſuch thing, that the Devil never find us idle.</p>
            <p n="26">26. To go on in the way of virtue it is a good motive to conſider, that in this world there is no Purgatory for us, but either Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſe, or <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ell; becauſe he who ſerves God as he ought all labour and infirmity turns to his conſolation, and he hath within himſelf a Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſe; but he who doth the contrary, and giveth himſelf to ſenſuality, hath Hell in this world, and in the next.</p>
            <p n="27">27. The frequent Confeſſion of ſins brings
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:32173:35"/>great good to our ſoul; for it purifies, and heals, and confirms it in Gods ſervice. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore our ſet time to perform it muſt not be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred for any buſines whatſoever which may then occur: but firſt we ought to go to confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, and afterward about our affairs, in which we may hope for the better ſucceſs by this help.</p>
            <p n="28">28. Melancholly and trouble of mind brings great hurt to the ſpirit, whereas chearfulnes fortifies the heart, and makes one perſevere the better in a good life. Therefore the ſervant of God ought always to be chearful.</p>
            <p n="29">29. Scruples, becauſe they diſquiet the mind and make it melancholick, ought to be greatly ſhunned.</p>
            <p n="30">30. We muſt not ask of God temporal bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings, as health, riches, proſperity, and the like, abſolutely, but conditionally; if it pleaſe God, and if they be expedient.</p>
            <p n="31">31. When God beſtows on us any internal grace we ought not to dicloſe it except to our ſpiritual Father, otherwiſe we looſe it.</p>
            <p n="32">32. Who goeth to ſerve the ſick, or do o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther charities, muſt imagin ſuch a ſick perſon to be Chriſt, and all he doeth to him to be done to Chriſt himſelf; for ſo it is done with more love and benefit.</p>
            <p n="33">33. When any man doth a good work, and another aſcribes it to himſelf, and aſſumes the glory of it, he who did it ought exceedingly to rejoice, and acknowledge it a great favour from God, that others take that from him before
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:32173:35"/>men, becauſe he ſhall recover it with greater reward before God.</p>
            <p n="34">34. He doth ill who hath confidence of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf; and he who puts himſelf on the occaſion of a ſin, ſaying, I ſhall not fall, commonly doth fall with greater damage of his own ſoul: who would not fall let him not truſt to himſelf, nor preſume on his own ſtrength; but ſay to God, <hi>Lord, truſt not to me, nor expe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t any thing elſe of me but evil;</hi> and <hi>I ſhall aſſuredly fall if thou help me not.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="35">35. To keep far off all danger of impurity young men ought to fly carefully whatſoever (even the ſmalleſt) occaſion of this ſin. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore this H. man forbad his ſpiritual children to touch one another not ſo much as by the hands, altho but in jeſting.</p>
            <p n="36">36. When the ſoul reſigns it ſelf into the hands of God, and is contented with the divine good pleaſure, it remains in good hands, and is very ſecure that it will go well with it: and it belongs eſpecially to a ſick man to reſign over himſelf, and to ſay to God, <hi>Lord, if thou wilt have me, behold here I am; tho I have done no good at all, do with me what ſeems good unto thee.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="37">37. Who willeth any thing but Chriſt, knoweth not what he would have; who asketh any thing but Chriſt, knoweth not what he asketh; who worketh and not for Chriſt, knoweth not what he doth.</p>
            <p n="38">38. We muſt not be faſtned to any thing in this world, be it never ſo ſmall a matter: but we muſt be humbly affected amongſt the crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures,
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:32173:36"/>and deſire to have ſo low a condition as to ſtand in need of Six-pence, and, begging for it, to be denied it.</p>
            <p n="39">39. Who would have riches ſhall never have the Spirit.</p>
            <p n="40">40. The ſoul who gives it ſelf to God muſt be wholly God's; and what love is beſtowed on Parents and kindred, or on ſtudies, or on it ſelf, of ſo much love is God deprived.</p>
            <p n="41">41. The man who loves God with true love, and prizeth him above all things, ſometimes in his prayers meets with an overflowing of tears, and a concours of graces, or feelings of the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, in ſuch abundance that he is forced to beg an abatement.</p>
            <p n="42">42. One ought to reſerve for himſelf nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther place, nor time, when there is need to help his neighbour; and ought to quit his Spiritual guſts and his prayers for his neighbour, and leave Chriſt for Chriſt. And this is a great per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection, and few know how to do it.</p>
            <p n="43">43. When God's ſervant hath no troubles, nor any to perſecute him, and treat him inju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riouſly; if he would find the Spirit, let him imagin that ſome wicked man comes to affront him, and ſayeth much villany againſt him, and to injurious words addeth as uncivil deeds, beats him with a cudgel, or wounds him with a ſword, and with his fiſt makes his face black and blew; and being thus abuſed, then with great ſervency of love in imitation of Chriſt let him incline his heart to pardon the wrong that is done him, and overcoming all angry motions
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:32173:36"/>that may ariſe, and not willing for the love of God to take any revenge let him with great love forgive him, as if he had truly received ſuch an injury; that by the frequent practice of ſuch imaginations the heart may accuſtom it ſelf to pardon a real injury; as the ſouldier, who learns to play at foils, by accuſtoming him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf to handle his armes afterwards makes uſe of his art to fight in good earneſt.</p>
            <p n="44">44. Suffering Penance is ſtill neceſſary to the ſervant of God; and when ſtraightned with any affliction, then let him expect a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolation: for God never ſends an affliction, but that he ſends after it a conſolation: and in ſumme, the whole life of him, who ſerves God is nothing elſe but firſt a conſolation, and then another trouble.</p>
            <p n="45">45. When God viſits any man with an affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, and he hath not patience to bear it, it may be well ſaid unto him; Thou art not wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy of God's viſitation, nor deſerveſt ſo great a benefit.</p>
            <p n="46">46. When there come againſt us tribulati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, infirmities, and things much contrary to us, we are not timorouſly to fly them, but vali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>antly to overcome them; becauſe, if thou fly from any of them, another worſe will come up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on thee: who flies from a hoar-froſt will be covered with ſnow; who flies from a Bear meets with a Lion.</p>
            <p n="47">47. When God's ſervant goeth to receive in the Sacrament the glorious Body of Chriſt, in which are all the delights of heaven, he ought
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:32173:37"/>to ſtand in fear, and prepare himſelf more than ordinarily for future temptations; becauſe the marvelous Graces, which are conferred in that divine Sacrament, God will not have to lie idle; for Grace more abhors idlenes, than Nature doth vacuities.</p>
            <p n="48">48. When any one feels within his heart a new and extraordinary ſpirit, for the reaſon before mentioned let him ſtand prepared for ſome temptation and tribulation: and whilſt one feels in him this ardor of the Spirit, let him ask of God ſtrength to be able to endure whatſoever from heaven he ſhall be ordained to ſuffer, and that the temptation induce him not to any ſins, great, or little.</p>
            <p n="49">4<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. If any ſhould ask, what is the greateſt tribulation a true ſervant of God can have? It may be anſwered him, Not to have any tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bulation at all.</p>
            <p n="50">50. Let young men beware of the ſin of the fleſh, and old men of the ſin of avarice; the firſt is overcome by flying, the ſecond by re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſting.</p>
            <p n="51">51. A man muſt always ſtand in fear, and not truſt to himſelf, becauſe the Devil makes his aſſault unexpected, and darkens the under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding; and who ſtands not in fear is over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come, becauſe ſelf-confident he is deſtitute of the help of God.</p>
            <p n="52(1)">52<hi rend="sup">1</hi>. In the temptations which the laſcivi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſnes of the fleſh ſuggeſts to us let the tempt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed have recourſe inſtantly to God, and make thrice on his heart the ſign of the H. Croſs, and
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:32173:37"/>ſay; <hi>Chriſt, thou Son of God, have mercy on me;</hi> or the verſe of the Pſalm, <hi>O God make ſpeed to ſave me, O Lord make haſt to help me;</hi> or this, <hi>Create in me a clean heart O God, and renew a right ſpirit within me;</hi> and let him kiſs the earth, and ſay to the tempter, <hi>I will accuſe thee to my ſpiritual Father if thou tempteſt me any more.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="52(2)">52<hi rend="sup">2</hi>. Obedience againſt our inclinations is to be practiſed in ſmall matters, and which ſeem of no conſequence; becauſe thus we attain a fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cility to yeild it in greater.</p>
            <p n="52(3)">52<hi rend="sup">3</hi>. The mortification of the will and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding in matter of obedience to Superi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ors is much more beneficial, and attains ſooner to perfection, than great corporal Penances.</p>
            <p n="52(4)">52<hi rend="sup">4</hi>. It is not ſufficient to conſider, if God will have ſuch good done as is attempted, but if he will have it done by our means, in ſuch a manner, at ſuch a time: which appearing not to be God's will, we ought contentedly to deſiſt from any ſuch enterpriſe.</p>
            <p n="53">53. There is nothing better for man than Prayer, and without it he cannot endure long in the way of the Spirit; therefore every mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment muſt he have recourſe to this moſt pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erful means of Salvation.</p>
            <p n="54">54. The enemy of our ſalvation fears no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing more, nothing makes him ſadder, no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing he ſeeks more to hinder, than Prayer.</p>
            <p n="55">5<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. When one is praying, let not his bodily eyes be ſo fixed on an Image that he never re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moves them from it, for this will hurt the
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:32173:38"/>Head; but let him make uſe of an Image for the help of his memory: as, for example, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce into his mind the benefit of the Incarna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Chriſt, or his Nativity, or his death on the Croſs; or if it be the Image of a holy man, or a holy woman, let him make uſe of it to put him in mind of their virtues, that he may imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate them, and pray them to intercede to God for him.</p>
            <p n="56">56. To know how to pray well, it is a very great help to read the Lives of Saints, and when the Spirit inclines him then to meditate on them; and ſo when it inclines to think on the paſſion of Chriſt then to follow that at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traction; and not to pray or meditate diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rently from that to which the Spirit moves.</p>
            <p n="57">57. Fancies, which intervene, are a great diſturbance to prayer; and many troubled with ſuch by-thoughts give it over: but they do not well; for, notwithſtanding any ſuch fancies, one ought to perſevere ſtill, as much as may be, in prayer; and God often gives in a moment that which could not be obtained in a long time.</p>
            <p n="58">58. Amongſt other things, we are to ask of God, a chief is perſeverance in well-doing, and well-ſerving of God; becauſe if any hath pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience and perſeverance in well doing in a good life after once begun, he will acquire an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding great meaſure of Spirit.</p>
            <p n="59">59. In the beginning of the converſion of a ſoul to God the Spirit uſeth to come ſometimes ſtrongly upon him; but afterward it ſeems as it were to go away, and the Lord ſhews thereby
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:32173:38"/>as if he had forſaken him; but ſtand he firm, and it will return again</p>
            <p n="60">60. God uſeth almoſt never to ſend death to one who much ſerves him, but that he firſt noti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fies it to him by ſome ſign, or by giving him the Spirit extraordinarily.</p>
            <p n="61">61. There are three degrees in a Spiritual life: the firſt is called an animal life; the ſecond, the life of a man; the third, the life of an An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gel; that is to ſay, the Lord uſeth in the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning, for the drawing of ſouls to himſelf, to entice them with ſweetnes, and with a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain ſpirit and guſts extraordinary, and then afterward he makes a ſhew to go far from them, witholding his moſt holy hand from theſe ſweet treatments, to ſee if they ſtand firm in the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, leaving them to fight it out for a little time; and then when they have made reſiſtance for a while, and have overcome thoſe tribulations and temptations, he reſtores afterward their heavenly guſts and conſolations doubled; and this is a life Angelical, void of all pain or of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence.</p>
            <p n="62(1)">62<hi rend="sup">1</hi>. It is no pride to deſire to exceed in ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>city any Saint whatſoever; becauſe to deſire to be Saint is to deſire we may have the will to love and to honour God above all things: and this deſire, if it were poſſible, ought to be extended to infinity, becauſe God is worthy of infinite love, and becauſe his greatneſs is infinite.</p>
            <p n="62(2)">62<hi rend="sup">2</hi>. No man ever ought to truſt his own prudence, but in all things to ask counſel of God, conſult his Confeſſor, and beg the pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers of others.</p>
            <pb n="74" facs="tcp:32173:39"/>
            <p n="63">63. To maintain our ſelves in a good life, and the holy ſervice of God, frequent Confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion and the holy Communion are moſt neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry; for the right practiſing of theſe is a very great help.</p>
            <p n="64">64. For Graces obtained by the way of prayer, we muſt continue ſo long our prayer till the grace be perfected; and if prayer be inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted God doth ſometimes ſuſpend the grace. Therefore if a ſick man, for whom prayer is made, begin to mend upon the prayers made for him, theſe then muſt not be ceaſed; but as ſuch recovery was begun by prayer, even ſo by the ſtrength of prayer muſt it be perfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted.</p>
            <p n="65">65. When he, who prayeth, feels in the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuation of his prayer great quietneſs of ſpirit, it is a good ſign, that God either hath or will grant the grace he ſues for.</p>
            <p n="66">66. Many feeling within themſelves carnal temptations, or the like, doubt ſometimes whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they have conſented or no; but if the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon tempted feel in himſelf ſtill a love toward that vertue againſt which he was tempted, and an hatred againſt that vice; it is a ſign he hath not conſented. Likewiſe if he would not ſwear that he hath conſented, it is a ſign that he hath not conſented; becauſe when there is a delibe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate conſent, the ſoul eaſily perceives it.</p>
            <p n="67">67. After the temptation paſt we muſt not reaſon if we have conſented, or not; for ſuch reaſonings cauſe a return of carnal temptations.</p>
            <p n="68">68. Carnal temptations ought to be feared
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:32173:39"/>and fled even in ſickneſs, and in old age it ſelf, ſo long as we are able to ſhut and open our eyes; for the ſpirit of fornication ſpares neither time nor perſon.</p>
            <p n="69">69. The ſervant of God, if with more ſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity he will walk amongſt ſo many ſnares ſpread abroad in all places, let him have for an inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſor for him to her Son the Bl. Virgin.</p>
            <p n="70">70. Church-goods muſt be employed ſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ringly, and not be ſpent but upon neceſſity, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they are goods which belong to God.</p>
            <p n="71">71. Chearfulneſs and mirth is good in him who ſerves God, but he muſt file diſſolutenes, and be careful not to fall into a ſpirit of jeſting; for they who delight in jeſting render them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves incapable of ever receiving the Spirit of God, and if they have any thing that is good in them, they loſe it ſuddenly.</p>
            <p n="72">72. When the Prieſt viſits the ſick let him not play the Prophet, ſaying, that the ſick per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon will not recover; becauſe ſometimes having propheſied death, if the ſick become well again he is diſpleaſed that he hath erred in his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecy.</p>
            <p n="73">73. A Confeſſor is to be choſen with ſerious deliberation, for it is a great advantage to have a good guide in ſo difficult a way; but having choſen one he is not eaſily to be changed, but to be believed and conferred-with about our oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>currences, becauſe God will never permit that a Confeſſor ſhould err in a thing that might be a hinderance to the ſoul of a Penitent.</p>
            <p n="74">74. To profit by reading the lives of Saints,
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:32173:40"/>or other Spiritual books, we muſt not read them with curioſity, or in haſt, but by little and little; and when any feels himſelf touched, or that ſome devotion ariſeth in him, he muſt go no further, but ſhut the book and there ſtop, and hearken to the Spirit; and when it fails, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn to his Reading.</p>
            <p n="75">75. To pray well the ſoul muſt firſt bring it ſelf into a moſt profound humility, and know it ſelf unworthy to ſtand before ſo great a Majeſty, and to ſhew to God its neceſſities and its weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and being humbled caſt it ſelf on God, that he may teach it to pray.</p>
            <p n="76">76. When any man remains liſtleſs and all-diſcontented, or feels his ſenſual appetite trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleſom and frequent, he muſt not loſe courage: becauſe when God will beſtow any virtue, he permits a temptation of the contrary vice; that by fighting and reſiſting a man may make himſelf capable of that virtue, againſt which he was aſſaulted.</p>
            <p n="77">77. It is not fitting to leave off doing any good work becauſe one feels ſome riſing of vain-glory; becauſe as often as Vain-glory is not the Miſtris but a companion of the work, it takes not away the worth of the work, tho perfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is in this that it be a ſervant.</p>
            <p n="78">78. Whoſoever deſires to live in a ſtrict way of Religion, let him firſt learn to ſubdue his will in ſome things wherein he finds greateſt oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition, becauſe thus with more facility he ſhall perſevere.</p>
            <p n="79">79. When any one of his own accord would
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:32173:40"/>faſt, uſe diſcipline, wear ſack-cloth; or the like, and his Confeſſor doth not like it; the Confeſſor ought not to be violently urged to give any ſuch licence.</p>
            <p n="80">80. Let a man ſtay in his own houſe, <hi>i. e.</hi> within himſelf, and not become a <hi>Syndick,</hi> or Judge of the actions and lives of others; if he deſires not to make raſh judgments, nor to murmur at, nor to deſpiſe, his neighbour.</p>
            <p n="81">81. A young Convert is not to ſeek to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vert others, but to be careful to confirm him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, and to make himſelf ſtrong againſt temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations, and to be humble, and not to think he hath done any great matter, but rather to eſteem himſelf to have done nothing, that he fall not into pride.</p>
            <p n="82">82. Scrupulous perſons are in all things whatſoever to depend upon their ſpiritual Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and not truſt their own judgment; other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe they will never be able to deliver them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves; they may well find a truce, but not a peace.</p>
            <p n="83">83. A man, who ſerves God, muſt remain reſigned to feel the guſts of the things of God, and to want them; to entertain chearfulneſs and ſadneſs.</p>
            <p n="84">84. It is a thing very dangerous to ſpiritual perſons to deſire to ſee viſions; and many, who have followed after ſuch a ſpirit, have fallen into great ruine.</p>
            <p n="85">85. To cure any one, who hath fallen into ſome ſin after a vertuous life led for a long time, there is no greater means to reduce him to his
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:32173:41"/>firſt condition, than to make him do ſome emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent mortification: that is to make him diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover his fault to ſome others of a ſingular good life, with whom he hath ſome intimacy, in whom he may confide; becauſe by ſuch humili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty God will raiſe him up to his former eſtate again.</p>
            <p n="86">86. All men are much concerned in the quiet of their own conſcience; therefore if any would make ſome particular vow, the Holy Man thought it good for the moſt part that it ſhould be made conditional; as thus, <hi>If I can; If I remember,</hi> or in ſome ſuch manner.</p>
            <p n="87">87. In every thing and for every thing we ought to throw our ſelves into the hands of our Lord: for if God will have us to do nothing more than we do, yet he will make us good in that which we do.</p>
            <p n="88">88. A Religious man, who is in an Order fallen away from its ancient diſcipline, and findeth in himſelf great gifts of the ſpirit, ought not to leave his own Order, to enter into ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, but to abide therein: for God will make uſe of him towards the reforming of his Order by his good Example.</p>
            <p n="89">89. We muſt not be ſwift in adviſing our brother concerning his defects and wants; but firſt we are to conſider our ſelves, afterwards others; and to do it with much prudence.</p>
            <p n="90">90. Every man ought ſo live to holily every day, and to frame all his actions in ſuch a man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, as if that ſhould be his laſt day.</p>
            <p n="91">91. If thou loveſt all men with true love,
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:32173:41"/>thou canſt never bear hatred to any man; nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther for words ſpoken againſt thee, nor for diſ-curteſies received; for in a heart, where there is not love to our neighbour whomever, there God is not.</p>
            <p n="92">92. Who perceives ſome diſcontentedneſs in himſelf ought not to be troubled at it; for it will quickly paſs over; but in the mean-while to overcome ſuch an ill paſſion he muſt ſay his prayers, or ſing ſome ſpiritual Hymn of praiſe.</p>
            <p n="93">93. We muſt be ready to obey the will of our Superiors, and to do rather the will of another than our own.</p>
            <p n="94">94. Whoſoever deſires that Chriſt ſhould give him the firſt place in heaven, let him be well pleaſed to ſtand always in the laſt place here on earth; and when any one perceives himſelf deſpiſed let him thank God for it, hoping that honor is reſerved for him in heaven.</p>
            <p n="95">95. Let all things be taken in good part, and judge not other mens actions; but learn to have compaſſion on our neighbours defects; thinking with our ſelves, that if God did not hold his hand upon our head we ſhould do worſe: and he who hath any good parts let him not be proud, but give thanks to God, from whom cometh every good.</p>
            <p n="96">96. We muſt ſeek Chriſt where he is not, <hi>i. e.</hi> in Croſſes, and Tribulations, where now our Redeemer, who is crowned with glory, is not to be found; and when any falls into Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bulations, he muſt not complain; becauſe they
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:32173:42"/>are ſent from God our moſt loving Father and moſt merciful Lord, to procure us the greater crown in heaven</p>
            <p n="97">97. Every day for ſome ſhort time read ſome ſpiritual book, and be careful to retain in memory ſome particular point which may be profitable to your ſoul.</p>
            <p n="98">98. When there is occaſion to buy any thing none ought to be moved with affection to it, but with the need or want of it; and the holy Man uſed on ſuch occaſions to ſay; <hi>I buy not affections.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="99">99. At the time of receiving the Holy Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion we ſhould beg a remedy againſt that vice we find our ſelves moſt inclined to.</p>
            <p n="100">100. When any one viſits the Altars let him ask from the Saints of theſe Altars a ſpiritual Alms; this being a good way to acquire the Spirit and Devotion.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="81" facs="tcp:32173:42"/>
            <head>Concerning the INSTITUTION of the Society of <hi>JESUS.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>THey have three years in all of Novitiat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip; two before entring on their Stu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies; one after theſe are finiſhed.</p>
            <p>In their Novice-ſhip much accuſtomed to Mental Prayer; Examens of their Meditations, and of Conſcience; being obliged to manifeſt all their good as well as evil thoughts and ſug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſtions to their Superiors, that theſe may be able to make a perfecter judgment of them, and more aptly guide them. Much practiſed in all mean employments; as, ſerving in Hoſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tals, tending on the ſick, begging alms from door to door. In the houſe doing all under-offices, helping in the Kitchin, ſweeping rooms, car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rying wood, ſerving the table <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Having no extraordinary faſts or other mortifications appointed them; but in all theſe directed as the Maſter of the Novices thinks fit.</p>
            <p>After the two years of their Novice-ſhip ſeven years are to be ſpent in their ſtudies, after having firſt learnt the languages: three in Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophy and Mathematicks, four in School-Divinity.</p>
            <pb n="82" facs="tcp:32173:43"/>
            <p>During their ſtudy of Divinity often practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed in domeſtick preaching, that they may ſo acquire a facility therein.</p>
            <p>After the four years ſpent in School-Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinity they are allowed two years for private ſtudy in Theology; and for giving account of their former Studies in performing of publick diſputations and exerciſes. Then they paſs through a third year of Novice-ſhip or Proba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; and after this again are allowed one year more (if they be deſigned for preaching) for the ſtudy of the Holy Scriptures, and of the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, and for Meditation: Or two years for this, if allowed none before for reviewing their former ſtudies. One reaſon given for this in <hi>Inſtruct.</hi> 2. of the 7th <hi>Congreg. pro Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cionat.</hi> is, — <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nde</hi> (ſay they) <hi>illud etiam com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modum ſequetur, quod tantopere aliorum concioni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus deſcribendis non inhiabunt. Vid. Reg. Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vincial.</hi> 52. <hi>Inſtruct.</hi> 7. <hi>Congreg. pro Concionan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tibus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Their chief imployments after their ſtudies finiſhed, and a third year of Novitiat-ſhip paſſed thro, are.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Teaching the Chriſtian Doctrine to Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren and common people, eſpecially on Holy days, when they are more eaſily aſſembled. The Fathers-profeſſed and more ancient doing this office, as well as others. <hi>Ignatius</hi> did it when General.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Teaching to children and ſtudents the languages, Rhetorick, and Humanity; then Philoſophy and Mathematicks; and laſtly Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinity.
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:32173:43"/>In which obliged never to be ſingular in their opinions, nor broach any new, not formerly taught by approved authors.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Preaching. For which the chief pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parations, they are directed to, are, <hi>Reg. Concion.</hi> 4. <hi>Lectioni ſacrae Scripturae ac Patrum praecipue, incumbere. Videre peculiari ſtudio Evangelia toto anno occurrentia, &amp; in eis ea quae uſui eſſe poſſunt adnotare; itemque compendium facere ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicationis rerum ad fidem &amp; christianam vitam neceſſariarum</hi> [this chiefly for their teaching the <hi>Doctrina Chriſtiana]: <hi>atque in communes locos redigere omnia, quae ad virtutum commendationem &amp; vitiorum deteſtationem pertinent.</hi> Or as in the <hi>Constit.</hi> 4. <hi>p.</hi> 8. <hi>c.</hi> §. 3. <hi>Praevidere quod in vitiorum detestationem inducit, &amp; remedia eiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem applicanda: ſicut è contrario, quae ad praecepta, ad virtutes, ad bona opera pertinent: tum ea, quae movere poſſunt ad illa amanda; &amp; media etiam ad eadem conſequenda: &amp; haec in compendium, ſi fieri potest, redacta utiliora eſſe, ne tam multis libris opus ſit.</hi> Likewiſe for to render them the more fit for their employment they are directed often to hear good preachers, and to peruſe the treatiſes of ſuch <hi>de modo concionandi:</hi> and all the Society are practiſed early to make probation Sermons in their Colleges, at meals, in the Refectory, and at other times, whilſt yet Students in Divinity, and before they be in ſacred Orders; another giving them their ſubject, and directing them to matter. See <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtit.</hi> 3. p. 1. c. 2 and 5 §. So in the fifth rule <hi>Concionat.</hi> they are enjoined <hi>in concionibus domi,
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:32173:44"/>vel in aliiis locis minus frequentibus, ſe exercere.</hi> Again. In their Sermons they are required (<hi>Reg. ib.</hi> 9.) Iis praecipue inſistere, quae ad christianans institutionem, atque ad extirpanda vitia &amp; vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutes inſerendas valent. Commendare populo Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſionis &amp; Euchariſtiae frequentem uſum, in bonis operibus profectum &amp; perſeverantiam; eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carum caeremoniarum obſervationem; obedientiam Principibus &amp; Praelatis, qui Dei in terris vices gerunt: Commendare etiam illis peculiari ratione poenitentiae &amp; miſericordiae opera; ſanctarum pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cum &amp; aliarum piarum devotionum exercitia; uttlium librorum lectionem; filiorum bonam edu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cationem. Reg.</hi> 10. they are inſtructed <hi>modum concionandi a Scholaſtico diverſum eſſe debere, &amp; ita ad docendum comparatum, ut ad animorum motum praecipue dirigatur; non ita exacte pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ponere argumenta, quibus contraria pars confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matur; ſed tamen eo pacto rem exponere, ut audir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tores ex datâ explicatione ſolutionem eorum quae ſibi in mentem venerint, aut ab aliis audiverint, facile colligant. Epiſt. Generalium</hi> 16. §. 10, 11. And <hi>Induſt.</hi> 5. they are required <hi>Aliquid ſibi certo conſtituere, quod perſuadeant, &amp; rationes afferre, quibus id confirment, amplificent, exagge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent, &amp; moveant audientes. Inſtare perſuaden do &amp; inculcando</hi>  
               <hi>&amp; non multa curſim dicere ad copiam oſtendendam, ne concionator jejunus ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pareat. Quaſi vero inſistere ſingulis</hi> [mutatis rationibus &amp; ſtimulis] <hi>prolatis exemplis &amp; ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionibus à ſimilibus &amp; diſſimilibus, &amp; argumentis à</hi> majori, <hi>&amp; e contra,</hi> ab utilitate, delectatione, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>acilitate &amp;c, <hi>tum etiam loco &amp; tempore ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turis
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:32173:44"/>expendendis</hi> &amp;c <hi>non arguat copiam.</hi> They are warned <hi>Ibid. ad vit andam oſtentationem, ejuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ve ſuſpicionem,</hi> not to criticize too much on the ſignification of words, or infer other ſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence little to their purpoſe. Warned (<hi>Reg. Concionat.</hi> 9) <hi>a rerum ſubtilium curioſâ tracta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tione abſtinere.</hi> Warned (Reg. 20.) <hi>Non eſſe affectatos, aut verborum lenocinia ſectari, nec ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dio-politioris ſermonis</hi> &amp;c <hi>ſaeculare aliquid redo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lere.</hi> (Reg. 21.) <hi>In laudibus &amp; reprehenſionibus, animique exaggerationibus abſtinere: vocem, ubi non eſt opus, non praeter modum extollere, aut de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>primere. (Reg. 16.) <hi>Cavere, ne facetiis aut inutilium rerum narratione concionem contempti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilem faciant.</hi> (Reg. 12, 13.) to forbear in their Sermons reprehenſions of great perſons (Magiſtrates, or Prelates) other Religious Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, or their own, or any private perſon; but to reprehend vice in a general manner, and ſo as the vice may not be particularly faſtened upon any. (<hi>Ep Gen.</hi> 16. <hi>Induſt.</hi> 7.) Not to write their whole Sermon and then <hi>verbatim</hi> get it by heart. <hi>Nam,</hi> (ſaith <hi>Aquaviva</hi>) (praeter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quam quod ut populus probe intellig at ac percipiat quod dicitur, verſandum eſt, quod agitur, multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modâ ratione dicendi; quod in poteſtate non habent, qui praeparata &amp; ad verbum memoriter retenta pronunciant) certum eſt, dici efficaciter eo modo &amp; penitus inſeri vix quidquam poſſe Id vero ſi animadvertat Auditor (quod proclive eſt) tum certe illud tanquam ſerium, aut ex animo dictum non habet, nec magni facit. Adde quod oratio artificioſe contexta &amp; claborata ſeipſam prodit;
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:32173:45"/>ſemperque veretur Concionator, ne, ſi vel una pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riodus aut etiam particula memoriâ excidat, totus ruat orationis contextus. Quaeres quantopere di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cendi vim retardet credi vix poteſt.</hi> Laſtly ſuch, as teach others, are required in their own life to be ſingularly exemplary.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Confeſſing people, and adminiſtring the Sacraments. For Confeſſions certain Prieſts are appointed, at certain hours, every day, or thoſe more ſolemn, to ſit in the Church to hear them. The Confeſſors are required <hi>Reg. Sacerdot.</hi> 11. <hi>In caſibus conſcientiae iiſque prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſertim, qui ad cenſuras, caſus reſervatos, reſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutiones, pertinent, ſeſe diligenter exercere; earum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que rerum compendia, &amp; brevem interrogandi me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thodum</hi> [for helping the penitents to diſcover their ſins] <hi>ac, contra ſingulorum peccatorum ſpecies, exempla &amp; dicta Sanctorum, atque alia ſalutaria remedia ſtudere comparare. Inter ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ipſos conformes eſſe, &amp; aliorum Confeſſariorum exiſtimationi unumquemque conſutere.</hi> To carry themſelves equally, in receiving Confeſſions, to all Conditions. For women, to ſhew them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to them rather ſevere than familiar; and to render their Confeſſions as ſhort as may be, by cutting off impertiuencies; not to take again their General Confeſſions, if formerly made. To avoid looking upon the Confeſſed, their hand being interpoſed, where nothing elſe<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Forbidden, to adviſe their Penitents to the taking of Religious Vows, or to enter into one Order of Religious, rather than other; or to communicate more frequently than once
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:32173:45"/>in eight days. See theſe things in <hi>Reg. Sacerd.</hi> and in the <hi>Inſtruct Congreg.</hi> 7. <hi>pro Confeſſariis.</hi> Several inſtructions are drawn up (<hi>Ordinat. General.</hi> 11. c.) for the Confeſſors of Princes, which theſe Confeſſors are obliged to obſerve: which inſtructions are alſo ſhewed to the Prince, and ſuch obligation declared to him.</p>
            <p n="5">5. Giving the Spiritual Exerciſes to any per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons whatſoever deſiring to perform them: but all or only ſome part of them according to the condition and capacity of the perſon: They having in every Houſe and College a chamber, one of the moſt ſolitary and retired, fitted for it. Theſe Exerciſes are a Body of ſelect Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations, Directions, and Rules ſo ordered and adminiſtred to the Meditant as that each of them may have a right place for a more effectu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al operation upon the Soul fitly prepared by the former. All together tending to the effect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of its ſpeedy Converſion from a bad life to a good: or from a good to one yet better and more perfect: As alſo to the preſent e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lection of a better State or Condition of life than its former hath been; or, (where no reaſon, or at leaſt liberty, to change this) to a better management or improvement of it. To all which the Meditant is chiefly excited by the perfect example and pattern of the life of our Lord frequently propoſed to him in theſe ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tual exerciſes The Meditant, for the ſpace of a month, or fortnight, or leſs time, as other affairs permit, retires to a private room, ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſtring himſelf from all company, ſave one
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:32173:46"/>that at certain times brings him his diet and other neceſſaries, and his Director in the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſes; in this retirement alſo medling with no other employment or Books, tho pious, ſave only the Exerciſes; nor pre-occupating any thing in theſe, or doing in any other order, than is from time to time preſcribed. His Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rector viſits him once a day, or (if need re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire) oftener: and from time to time gives him in writing the matter of his preſent Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations; after he hath firſt delivered him ſome General Rules and Method how to perform them. And he again is to return to his Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rector a punctual account of all that paſſeth in his Soul whether conſolatory or deſolatory in them; which gives his Director light in what way beſt to proceed with him for the future; who detains him for a longer or ſhorter time in exerciſes of the ſame king (tho varyed al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways in ſome particulars) or alſo changeth them, according to his different proficiency. In ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral practiſing him alſo in ſome parts only of the Exerciſes, and wholly omitting others, according to the condition, preſent capacity, knowledge, advancement in vertue and piety of the perſon exerciſed. Five hours of Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation are deſigned every day, or (where ſome debility) four. The firſt at mid night, he ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing then to perform it. The ſecond early in the morning. The third not long before din<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner. The fourth in the Afternoon. The fifth toward the Evening. Every Meditation is to be concluded with a reverend Colloquy to
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:32173:46"/>God, or our Lord Chriſt <hi>&amp;c,</hi> as a Criminal with his Judge, or a Servant with his Lord, or a Son with his Father, or alſo a Friend with his Friend, complaining before him of his preſent faults or infirmities, requeſting ſome Grace, asking his counſel, craving his help. After every Meditation a quarter of an hour is alot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for recollecting the chief paſſages of it; as alſo two of the five daily Meditations are only Repetitions of the former, for fixing them more in his thoughts, and alſo enlarging theſe on the things therein, which moſt affected him. The Meditant alſo in this retirement, after ſufficiently prepared, makes a general Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion of the ſins of his former life, but this thought fit to be heard by ſome other Prieſt rather than his Director.</p>
            <p n="6">6. Aſſiſting Hoſpitals, the Sick, the Impri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoned; both for their ſpiritual and coporal ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſities.</p>
            <p n="7">7. Miſſions to plant Chriſtian Religion, or repair and augment, wherever their Superiors ſhall ſend them. The manner of the Miſſion this, Some choſen Fathers profeſſed, after the manner of Apoſtles, two together, and on foot, if neceſſity require not the contrary, without much luggage (See <hi>Ep. Gen.</hi> 7. §. 4.) are ſent forth into ſuch places, as are thought to have much need of Inſtruction, of which places they have a Catalogue given them to ſtay in each, as they diſcern its profiting by them (eſpecially to go in <hi>vicos &amp; caſtella minori hominium fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quentiâ habitata, &amp; proinde opis illius magis in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diga,</hi>
               <pb n="90" facs="tcp:32173:47"/>ſaith <hi>Aquaviva Ibid.</hi>) Leave is firſt ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained from the Ordinary. Their expence is diſcharge by the Society, (that no offence from hence be taken) ſave only lodging, which they are to take up rather in ſome Hoſpital, if ſuch convenience be, or elſe, where the Parſon of that place ſhall appoint; only it to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mote from women. Their employments (af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter firſt having applied themſelves to the Cler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy of that place to obtain their good will and aid; and after having firſt diſcourſed to the people being aſſembled, of the neceſſity of the Chriſtian Doctrine, and of the great evils that accompany the ſtate of mortal ſin, whereby may be apprehended the neceſſity of Confeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on) are theſe. In the morning to hear Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſions; having alſo ſeveral Priviledges and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulgences granted to them by the Pope. In the Afternoon to teach the Chriſtian Doctrine to women and children, requiring alſo from the children an account thereof; after Sun-ſet for an hour explaining the ſame Chriſtian Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine (the doctrine of the Trinity, the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles Creed <hi>&amp;c</hi>) to men, ſuppoſed then moſt at leiſure, only all women are excluded; beſides theſe employments, to reconcile differences and quarrels: To promote Confraternities <hi>Sanctiſſimi Sacramenti, Roſarii, Doctrinae Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianae</hi> &amp;c. To give the ſpiritual Exerciſes to Clergy or others deſiring them; and in other things alſo to direct the Clergy, Schools, <hi>&amp;c,</hi> ſo far as they ſhall deſire, accept, or ſuffer it. See <hi>Instruct.</hi> 7. <hi>Congreg General. pro Miſſioni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qus</hi> §. 5.10.</p>
            <pb n="91" facs="tcp:32173:47"/>
            <p>No Stipends to be received for any of theſe functions, or for any other ſervice of the So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciety either in Divinity, or humane Sciences; nor yet Alms, if given with relation to, and as a recompence of, ſuch Service; See <hi>Conſtit.</hi> 6. p. 2. c. 1. §. and in the firſt Canon of the fifth General Congregation this Conſtitution is made undiſpenſable. It is ordered likewiſe that no College may admit of any alms or gift in any reſpect, when they can once live on their own rents, unleſs ſuch gift or alms be for the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſing of the number of Students, or Prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptors. But firſt if alms be declared to be given them without any ſuch reſpect to their ſervice (in which the Donor may ſoon de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare himſelf) the Houſe of Fathers Profeſſed may accept it, for this Houſe lives wholly on Alms. Secondly, For Colleges alſo when en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowed in 3. <hi>Cong. Gen.</hi> Can. 7. 'tis conceded to the General to diſpenſe with them, alſo to accept ſuch alms and gifts, when not given as a recompence: and, accordingly, we find the General diſpenſing with them in <hi>Ord. Genera.</hi> 1. c. §. 14. by <hi>Claud. Aquaviva. Collegia quae poſſunt alere</hi> 12 <hi>ſcholares nullas eleemoſynas admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tere poſſunt, niſi levis momenti, raro, &amp; ab iis quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum timeatur offenſio ſi non admittantur. Reliqua</hi> [Collegia] <hi>poſſunt. Sed ſi ab iis mittantur, quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum filli ſcholas noſtras fequentant, &amp; conjectura ſit (ſumpto judicio ex circumſtantiis perſonarum, ac modo dandi &amp; loquendi) mitti pro compenſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tione, vel intuitu miniſterii, admitti non debent, donec plane intelligant accipi non poſſe, niſi nomine
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:32173:48"/>eleemoſynae ſecluſo omni alio reſpectu, atque hoc eo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem modo ipſi quoque largiantur</hi> [few Donors, that upon ſuch advertiſment will withdraw their gift, and not profeſs rather the admitta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble intention.] <hi>Idemque eſt judicium de eleemo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſynis, quae poſtquam noſtri alicubi concionati ſunt, ad domos vel Collegia interdum mittuntur a Prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latis, vel a civitatius, aut aliis.</hi> He that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſeth any is enjoined alſo <hi>Reg. Sacerd.</hi> §. 22. <hi>non accipere quidquam ſive ab iis quorum confeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ones audiverit, ſive ab aliis, quod vel in pauperes diſtribuat, vel alteri ſatisfactionis nomine reſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuat, niſi ſuperior, cum opus eſſet, ſecus faciendum judicaverit.</hi> All gifts <hi>&amp;c</hi> ſent to any particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar perſon may only be applied to the common uſe, <hi>Reg.</hi> 60. <hi>Rector.</hi> Alſo to avoid all ſhew of Avarice they may retain in their Churches no Alms-Cheſt or Box, whether for themſelves or others. <hi>Conſt.</hi> 6. p. 2. c, 8. §.</p>
            <p>In times of Infection, for peforming to ſuch perſons all neceſſary duties, the Superior pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſeth the matter to his Society, and out of thoſe who offer themſelves chooſeth thoſe whom he thinks fitteſt.</p>
            <p>None ordinarily made Prieſt till ten years experience had of him: that is till two or three years after he hath finiſhed the courſe of his Studies. None Profeſſed and taking the fourth vow of obedience to the Popes Miſſion, till (ordinarily) ſeventeen or eighteen years ſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; and then his ability firſt approved by ſome ſworn examiners for teaching Philoſophy and Divinity with applauſe.</p>
            <pb n="93" facs="tcp:32173:48"/>
            <p>To the three Vows taken by other Orders many qualifications and reſtrictions are added by the Founders of this Society.</p>
            <p>Firſt concerning them in general. Theſe Vows are taken with a reſervation, that the General may releaſe them, whereby perſons unfit or ſcandalous may at any time be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moved, or alſo the male-content, if they can obtain the Generals conſent, releaſed.</p>
            <p n="2">2. For Poverty: Firſt, as none may have any thing of his own, ſo of what they have in common, all fare alike; the Seniors and the General himſelf, as the Servants; for clothes, lodging, and employments, even in perform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the meaneſt offices, all alike; none ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>empted, not the General himſelf, but that they are ſometimes in the year to perform them for mortification and example ſake, <hi>Conſtit:</hi> 3. p. 1. c. 19. §. No difference made in ſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar priviledges, ſave the civil reſpect amongſt them, which is due to Age and Superiors. The General is regulated, <hi>in iis quae ad ſumptus &amp; ad curam corporis ejus attinent,</hi> by the Conſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of his four conſulters or aſſiſtants, whoſe order herein he is obliged to obey. <hi>Conſtit.</hi> 9. p. 5. c. 2. §. 4. c. 3. §. 2. They are pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibited to ſeek any preferments, either with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out or within the Society: or to admit of any offered, unleſs by the expreſs command of thoſe Superiors whom they are obliged to obey: and are bound to diſcloſe any other perſon whom they know to ſeek them. Which thing, as it cures ambition, and makes them wholly
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:32173:49"/>intend the common good of the Society, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in their ſtaff is for ever ſet up, ſo it preſerves the worthieſt perſons ſtill for the employment, the ſervice, and the government of the Society, who otherwiſe would be continually called out of it. It caſts them much upon writing, having noeccleſiaſtical, neceſſary, employments; nor being permitted to take any where any ſet <hi>cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ram animarum,</hi> or office in Church or Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth (<hi>Conſt.</hi> 4. p. 2. c. 4. §. 6. p. 3. c 5. §.) the reaſon, that ſo they may have more free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome firſt for their ſtudies; and ſecondly for more general ſervices of God and the Church. And laſtly it renders them more acceptable to, and more credited by, Princes and great men, becauſe they know, that theſe follow not any intereſts of their own; and renders alſo theſe perſons more free in their advice. 3. They are obliged not to meddle or entangle them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves in any ſecular affairs either of private perſons, or of Princes; or to ſide with any Prince more than other, in their ſecular dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferences or quarrels (<hi>Summar. Conſt. Reg.</hi> 43.) that ſo having the good will of all men, as not meddling in worldly matters, as likewiſe ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving their own thoughts the more free from theſe, they may proceed more proſperouſly in divine matters. See <hi>Canon. Congregationum Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neralium.</hi> Can 12, 13. of the fifth <hi>Cong.</hi> And 7. <hi>Cong.</hi> Can 13.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>4. All offices in the Society are beſtowed not by a <hi>major</hi> part of Votes (ſave only the election of the General) but by ſingle perſons: the higher by the General, the lower
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:32173:49"/>by the Provincial; the Society joyning ſome Conſulters or Aſſiſtants always to them, whoſe advice they are bound to hear, but not to fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low: which prevents all diſcord and factions, and more preſerves obedience to Superiors.</p>
            <p n="3">3. For Obedience; They are more left to the arbitrary power of their Superiors than any other Order: to which Superiors they are tied frequently to open all their mind and conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, and make known the good things thereof as well as the evil, and to be wholly at their ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitrary diſpoſal for their employments <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Only, in much doubt of any thing unlawful commanded, they may repair (firſt) to other judgments, who have the power to determin this unto them. See <hi>Conſtit.</hi> 6. <hi>part.</hi> 1. <hi>c.</hi> 1. <hi>n.</hi> — 3. <hi>part.</hi> 1. <hi>c.</hi> 23. §. — 8 <hi>p.</hi> 1. <hi>c. D.</hi> and ſee <hi>Ignatius</hi> his Life, 5. <hi>l.</hi> 4. <hi>c.</hi> And alſo in all other matters they may freely acquaint their Superiors with their wants, inconveniences, or neceſſities, with their deſires and inclinations, as alſo with the reaſons inducing them thereto; provided, that they have uſed prayer firſt about ſuch buſines. But, after ſuch propoſal, they are to acquieſce in ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence to what their Superior commands, unleſs he perhaps demand ſome further account from them of their own judgment or affections. See touching this <hi>Conſtit.</hi> 3. <hi>part.</hi> 2. <hi>c.</hi> 1. §. 6. <hi>part.</hi> 3. <hi>c.</hi> 1. §</p>
            <p n="4">4. For the preſerving of unity of opinion amongſt them, and ſo more peace and charity, they are enjoyned, in general, to conform to the doctrine of S. <hi>Thomas,</hi> (tho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> with the ſame
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:32173:50"/>liberty as others, called <hi>Thomiſts,</hi> have, as the 56. decree of the 5th. <hi>Gen. Cong.</hi> expounds the Conſtitution; <hi rend="sup">2</hi> in Divinity, not Philoſophy; <hi rend="sup">3</hi> nor in every thing for Divinity, [<hi>In quaeſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onibus mere Philoſophicis, aut etiam in iis quae ad Scripturas &amp; Canones pertinent, licebit ſequi etiam alios, qui eas facultates ex profeſſo tractaverunt.</hi> Thus the 5th. <hi>Gen. Congr.</hi>]) becauſe <hi>nullius hoc tempore doctrina occurrit, quae ſit eâ ſolidior, aut ſecurior:</hi> and to conform to the common tenents of the Church-Doctors, avoiding new opinions. For which cauſe alſo one and the ſame perſon (<hi>viz.</hi> the General) is appointed to licenſe all their printed Books. <hi>V. Conſtit.</hi> 4. <hi>p.</hi> 6. <hi>c.</hi> 17. §. Again every one, in any difference from com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon opinion, is obliged to ſubmit his judgment to the definition of the Society, <hi>i. e.</hi> in ſuch points as remain undefined by the Church. See <hi>Conſtit.</hi> 3. <hi>part.</hi> 1. <hi>c.</hi> 18. §. required alſo where the Doctors of the Church are contrary one to another, yet the Society therein alſo to endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour a conformity of opinion amongſt them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves; nay further, required to acquieſce in the judgment (tho contrary to theirs) of two or three, to whom they ſhall have firſt propoſed their reaſons, For thus runs the 6th. Rule di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctated by <hi>Ignatius,</hi> (<hi>Vid. S. Ignatii vit. per Riba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deneiram,</hi> 5. <hi>l.</hi> 4 <hi>c.</hi>) after his writing of his Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle of Obedience. <hi>Si quando tempus inciderit</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>quo mihi videatur à Superiore meo quid praecipi, quod contra conſcientiam meam ſit, Superi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ori vero aliud videatur; illi potius quàm mihi cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam, ſi quidem aperta ratio non repugnat. Quod ſi
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:32173:50"/>hoc in animum inducere non poſſum, at certè meum judicium ſenſum<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> relinquam, &amp; ad unius aut duo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum triumve judicium rem totam rejiciam, ut quod ab illis judicatum ſit, id ſequar: hoc ſi recuſo, lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſsime à perfectione abſum</hi> &amp;c. Again, the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſors and Readers required not to handle all queſtions, nor urge, or confute all objections; nor infer all arguments and reaſons; but in all theſe to omit thoſe unconſiderable or unprofita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble; alſo required (to give it in their own words) <hi>ut receptas jam, quamvis congruentes tan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum, rationes, quibus Fidei res probari ſolent, non refellant, nec temere novas excogitent, niſi ex con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stantibus ſolidiſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> principiis.</hi> So likewiſe not to teach or defend opinions, which may give great offence to the Catholicks of that place. Their words are: <hi>Quae opiniones, cujuſcun<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoris ſint, in aliqua Provincia aut Academia Catholicos graviter offendere ſcirentur, eas ibi non doceat aut defendat</hi> [Profeſſor]. <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>bi enim nec Fidei doctrina, nec morum integritas in diſcrimen adducitur, prudens charitas exigit, ut noſtri ſe il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lis accomodent, cum quibus verſantur.</hi> See for theſe things <hi>Ratio Studiorum, Regulae communes,</hi> and <hi>Reg. Profeſſorum Schol. Theol.</hi> They are requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red alſo <hi>ibid. ut de Conceptione B.</hi> Mariae, <hi>ac de ſolemnitate Votorum ſequantur ſententiam quae ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gis hoc tempore communis ſit, magiſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> recepta apud Theologos.</hi> Laſtly, in <hi>Summar. Conſtit. Reg.</hi> 42. They are required alſo <hi>judiciorum de rebus agen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dis diverſitatem (quae mater eſſe ſolet diſcordiae &amp; inimica unionis voluntatum) quantum fieri poteſt evitare.</hi> Likewiſe the Popes Supremacy over
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:32173:51"/>Princes being ſo ſtated by ſome Doctors, as hath given much offence; the 8th Congregation General (after the former Prohibitions of the Generals <hi>Aquaviva</hi> and <hi>Vitelleſchi</hi> to the Socie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to ſpeak or write any thing at all on this ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject) hath made this decree touching it: <hi>Ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus in virtute Sanctae Obedientiae, ne quis in poste<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum materiam de poteſtate Summi Pontificis ſuper Principes, eos deponendi</hi> &amp;c <hi>tractet, aut libris editis aut ſcriptis quibuſcunque, nec publice disputet aut doceat in Scholis, ut occaſiones omnes offenſionis &amp; querelarum praecidantur.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">5. For growing to perfection in their man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, and acquiring of all vertuous habits, as al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo for conſerving humility, they give their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, at their entrance into the Society, that any one (except only he that receives them in Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion) may inform their Superior of their faults, errors, and defects, or any other thing notable in them: To which purpoſe every one is asked in his firſt General Examination; <hi>An contentus ſit futurus, ut omnes errores &amp; defectus ipſius, &amp; res quaecunque, quae notatae in eo &amp; obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vatae fuerint, Superioribus per quemvis, qui extra confeſſionem eas acceperit, manifeſtentur.</hi> As like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe all are required ſo far to take care of one another as to diſcloſe them, when they think it neceſſary: which known, the Superior may uſe his endeavour toward that perſon for the rectifying thereof; but may not divulge the Informer, nor the fault, eſpecially if great. Mean-while none may reprehend another, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs the Superior, or one licenſed by him; of
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:32173:51"/>which thus the 31. <hi>Reg. Communis. Nemo prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter eos, quibus per Superiorem licet, quidquam aliis jubeat, alioſve reprehendat.</hi> Only they are required in <hi>Exam.</hi> 4. <hi>c.</hi> 8. §. <hi>boni conſulere ab a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liis corrigi, &amp; ad aliorum correctionem juvare, &amp; paratos eſse ſeſe invicem manifeſtare debito cum amore &amp; charitate ad majorem Spiritus profe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctum, praeſertim ubi à Superiore, qui illorum cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ram gerit, fuerit iis praeſcriptum.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Likewiſe beſides weekly Confeſſion, and the informations of others concerning their defects and faults, they are obliged, at leaſt once in ſix months, to render an account of their conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to their Superior, wherein they commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicate to him (<hi>ſub Sigillo,</hi> if they pleaſe) not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly their faults, but the whole ſtate of their ſouls, their contentednes in their condition, their proficiency in prayer, in the Spirit, in virtues; their temptations, impediments, anxieties, fears; their deſires, conſolations, joys, <hi>&amp;c,</hi> which may give their Superior more light how to proceed with them for the future, how to cure their infirmities, and advance them to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward perfection. See <hi>Summar. Conſtit. R.</hi> 40. and <hi>Reg. Mag. Nov.</hi> Obliged alſo, once in the year, for renewing of the Spirit, every one of how great employment ſoever, to retire himſelf for certain weeks or days, and repeat the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual Exerciſes.</p>
            <p>For Corporal Mortifications and Penances they have no ſet Rule, preſcribing theſe alike to all, as many other Orders, but are left to the arbitrement and direction of their Superior;
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:32173:52"/>who occaſionally appoints theſe to ſeveral per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons both for the kind and degree, differently, as he thinks fit. Which matter is thus order<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; becauſe the neceſſary employments im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed for the ſervice of their neighbour do re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire, as to many, eſpecially Seniors, the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion of theſe corporal afflictions, and ſome indulgence one way, to enable them for fati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gues in another; wherein they meet with far greater mortifications of the Spirit, in forego<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſome other contents and ſatisfactions of our nature, than thoſe of the fleſh amount to. For which imployment to fit them the better, the Juniors of the Society are prepared firſt with the Spiritual Exerciſes, retired from all humane converſation, with ſtricteſt <hi>Examens</hi> of Conſcience, General Confeſſions, many hours in the day Meditations; after this, the more to abaſe and humble them, with a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant ſervice for two or more months in the moſt vile and abject offices of the Houſe: Next, with being ſent to an Hoſpital for a month or longer times attendance of the ſick, enquiry alſo being made after their behaviour. Hence, ſent abroad on a pilgrimage, without mony or other humane aid for their ſubſiſtance, that lodging with the poor in Hoſpitals they may learn to forego the reſpects and honors of the world; and; begging their daily victuals, they may learn to wait and reſt wholly on the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Providence, and receive thankfully what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever good or bad treatment he affords them; and loſe all affection to the ſupport and ſupplies
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:32173:52"/>of their kindred, and not fear the extreameſt neceſſities of the loweſt ſecular condition. The ſubduing of our will in ſuch Spiritual appetites being both to all more beneficial, and to many much more difficult, than the ſubduing of it in the carnal.</p>
            <p>Frequent Letters, yearly, monthly, weekly, (as Rectors to the Provincials) to be ſent to Superiors, giving account of all ſpecial occur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents within and without the Society, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning all perſons in the Society, as well their Superiors as inferiors, (in which that all free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom may be uſed, their Letters are not to be opened), that ſo all may be kept in perfect o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience and co-intelligence; and all things being diſcovered, things amiſs may ſooner be rectified, good beginnings improved, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="6">6. For Solitude; They are prohibited to go to one anothers chambers, or to the gate to ſpeak with ſtrangers, without leave; as alſo en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joined to keep ſilence when meeting one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and when at table, (<hi>exceptis uſitatis ſalu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tationibus.</hi> Reg. Communes 27. —<hi>Niſi obiter &amp; perpaucis, aut de rebus neceſsariis.</hi> Reg. 26. —<hi>Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ve, in quibus loqui neceſse ſit.</hi> Reg. Magiſt. <hi>Novit.</hi> 79.) <hi>&amp;c,</hi> ſave at thoſe times of the day where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in conference is allowed, <hi>viz.</hi> the two hours of recreation after dinner and ſupper.</p>
            <p n="7">7. For Chaſtity; They are enjoined not to touch one another at all, tho but in jeſt; not to contract any particular familiarity or friendſhip with one more than other: not to go abroad without a companion and witneſs
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:32173:53"/>of their converſation: not to ſpeak with a woman, but that the other be preſent in the ſame room to ſee what they do, tho ſtanding out of diſtance to heart what they ſay: laſtly, to confeſs and communicate every week.</p>
            <p>Becauſe no rules ſo perfect, that they fit beſt all times and perſons, therefore moſt of the Conſtitutions of this Society left diſpenſable by the General, or his certain delegates, or alſo by the Provincials, as extraodinary occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions require.</p>
            <p>For the due execution of all the Conſtitutions and Rules of the Order, a Provincial is appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to viſit once every year every Houſe in his Province, reſiding in each for what time he ſeeth fit. And beſides this, in every particular Houſe there is appointed a Conſultation of the Governor and his Aſſiſtants in the beginning of every month concerning this matter; at which time is a Compendium or Memorial of them, and of other Ordinances of the Provincial or other Superiors read over, to ſee the better what is neglected: See for this <hi>Inſtructio</hi> 18. <hi>pro Executione urgendâ.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To the Governors of the Society are always joined a certain number of perſons for Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſulters; with whom the Governor is to adviſe in all matters of moment, but having heard them, to determin and execute what himſelf pleaſeth. One of which Conſulters is appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to be his Admonitor (but <hi>praemiſſâ oratione</hi>) concerning any thing which he thinks belong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth to his duty and office, or which is neglect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:32173:53"/>by him; yet chiefly concerning thoſe things which the Conſulters think meet to be told him; which Admonitor is faithfully to conceal his admonitions, yet, in much neglect of theſe by the Governor, he is obliged to acquaint the higher Superiors therewith. Letters directed to the Admonitors may not be opened by the Superiors. Theſe Conſulters are not elected by the Governor whom they aſſiſt, but by the next Superior, and thoſe of the General by the Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Congregation. See <hi>Regul. Conſultorum &amp; Admonitoris.</hi> And <hi>Conſtit.</hi> 9. p. 4. c. 4. §.</p>
            <p>The dangers incident to this moſt prudent and holy Order, upon their omitting ſolemn divine ſervice, ſeem to be theſe; their much converſe in and with the world; their being much tempted with gifts, by reaſon of their good ſervices to be publick; their liberty of diſpenſations and arbitrary government; their intentiveneſs to ſtudies and humane Sciences; their not having much preſcribed mortifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; the being intangled too much with ſecular affairs; the omiſſion of devotions and mortifications; the diminiſhing of the Spirit by proſecution of knowledge; the uſe of know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge to too much curioſity and hindrance of edification; the loſs of humility by the infla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of ſcience; the treſpaſſing againſt poverty in acquiring of wealth: tho it cannot be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied, that both by the fundamental Rules of the Society, and thoſe, ſince, both of the Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rals, and the General Congregations of this Order, all cautions are uſed for preventing
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:32173:54"/>theſe things, and for preſerving the primitive Spirit of the Society, that Chriſtian prudence can eaſily ſuggeſt, ſo that the Original deſigns of the Society be not laid aſide.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The Ordering of the Novices of the Jeſuites.</head>
               <p>IN the firſt Novice-ſhip their employments are thus ordered. They riſe every day at four of the clock in the morning (except on Saturdays, when they riſe at five) and have half an hour to dreſs themſelves and to make their beds, and to read over the ſubject of their following Meditation or Prayer.</p>
               <p>At half hour after four they betake themſelves to their Meditation or Prayer for one whole hour.</p>
               <p>The next half hour till ſix they ruminate and take notes of their precedent Prayer.</p>
               <p>At ſix they go to Maſs all together (except thoſe who are to ſerve at Maſs at ſome other time) which laſteth half an hour.</p>
               <p>The next half hour they betake themſelves again to their Chambers, and read ſome ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual book till ſeven. And then they go to Breakfaſt. Or elſe for one hour next after Maſs they are to be preſent at ſome Sermon, or ſome ſpiritual Conference; and thence they go to Breakfaſt.</p>
               <pb n="105" facs="tcp:32173:54"/>
               <p>At eight they do the work of the Houſe, <hi>i e</hi> Some carry wood, ſome ſweep the Chambers, ſome help the Cook in the Kitchin, ſome make clean the dining room, and lay the cloth, nap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kins, knives, and all neceſſaries for dinner: and theſe works they ſhare amongſt them.</p>
               <p>At nine they betake themſelves all to their Chamber till a quarter paſt ten, to read ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual Books.</p>
               <p>At a quarter paſt ten they learn ſomething without book for one half hour. At three quarters they make an Examen of their conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence till eleven.</p>
               <p>At eleven they go all to dinner (except thoſe that wait, who dine when the reſt have done.) From dinner they go all either into the Garden in Summer, or into ſome large Hall in the Win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, to diſcourſe together, and refreſh them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves after their Morning Recollection, till a quarter before one, and then for that quarter they hear the Saints Litanies.</p>
               <p>At one they betake themſelves all to their chambers to read till three, if there be no Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition of Catechiſm or Sermon at two.</p>
               <p>At three they do the ſame works that they do in the morning at eight, or ſuch like.</p>
               <p>At four they prepare themſelves for mental Prayer, which begins at the half hour after, and is continued till five.</p>
               <p>At five they ruminate, and take notes of their Prayer, till the half hour.</p>
               <p>At the half hour they go into the Church to pray and viſt the Bl. Sacrament of the Altar
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:32173:55"/>for one quarter; and thence they go into a great Hall, and walking recite their Roſary till half hour after ſix.</p>
               <p>Then they go to ſupper, and thence into the Garden or Hall, to refreſh themſelves after their afternoons Recollection till eight.</p>
               <p>At eight they betake themſelves to their Chambers, and read for half an hour: the next quarter examination of conſcience is to be made, and the laſt quarter they are to be all in bed by nine.</p>
               <p>On Sundays and Holy days at ſix of the clock after the firſt Maſs they all communicate; and then hear another Maſs in lieu of the Sermon or Conference on other days.</p>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               <pb facs="tcp:32173:55"/>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
